<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Oren Bochman&#39;s Blog</title>
<link>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.549</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Post With Code</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2024/post-with-code/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is a post with executable code.</p>
<div id="cf47d8ba" class="cell" data-execution_count="1">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display" data-execution_count="1">
<pre><code>2</code></pre>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>code</category>
  <category>analysis</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2024/post-with-code/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2024/post-with-code/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome To My Blog</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2024/welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is the first post in a Quarto blog. Welcome!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2024/welcome/thumbnail.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>thumbnail</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Since this post doesn’t specify an explicit <code>image</code>, the first image in the post will be used in the listing page of posts.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2024/welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AutoGluon Cheetsheets</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2023/autogluon/auto-gluon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://auto.gluon.ai/stable/index.html">AutoGluon</a> is a powerful framework for auto-ML.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2023/autogluon/autogluon-s.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>autogluon logo</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="tabular" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tabular">Tabular</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Innixma/autogluon-doc-utils/main/docs/cheatsheets/stable/autogluon-cheat-sheet.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Tabular</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="time-series" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-series">Time Series</h2>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Innixma/autogluon-doc-utils/main/docs/cheatsheets/stable/timeseries/autogluon-cheat-sheet-ts.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="multimodal" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="multimodal">Multimodal</h2>
</section>
<section id="multimodal-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="multimodal-1"><img src="https://automl-mm-bench.s3-accelerate.amazonaws.com/cheatsheet/stable/automm.jpeg" class="img-fluid" alt="Multimodal"></h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>cheatsheets</category>
  <category>code</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>auto ml</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2023/autogluon/auto-gluon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Recommended Books</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/2011-08-26-R_books.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Fellow data scientists, do not be overwhelmed by vast multiplicities of numbers, for they are but symbols of the natural order. Embrace their uncertainty and seek to understand the patterns within it. I offer you some of the first R books I came across. I got started with R in 2011, and I decided to update it to focus on stats and ml books I’ve come across with an attempt to list my favorites with their lecture notes and video lectures where available.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Software for data analysis: programming with R</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="chambers2008software">(Chambers 2008)</span> by <em>John Chambers</em> is an essential guidebook for those who wish to learn how to use the R programming language for data analysis. Chambers is a renowned statistician, and he shares his expertise in the field of data analysis through this book. The book covers a wide range of topics related to data analysis, including <code>data structures</code>, <code>object-oriented programming</code>, <code>graphics</code>, and <code>statistical modeling</code>. It also offers a practical approach to understanding R programming, with an emphasis on building applications that can handle large datasets. Overall, this is a valuable resource for those who want to learn about R programming for data analysis. It is a comprehensive guide that covers all the essential aspects of data analysis and provides hands-on experience with R programming. The book is written in a clear and concise manner, making it easy to follow even for beginners.</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/cover_software_for_data_analysis.webp" height="250"></p>
</div></div><ol start="2" type="1">
<li><strong>Principles of Statistical Data Handling</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="davidson-1996">(Davidson 1996)</span> data scientist, strive to understand the principles of statistical data handling with clarity and precision. The book offers a guide to the foundations of this field, including <code>exploratory data analysis</code>, <code>hypothesis testing</code>, and <code>model building</code>. Through careful attention and disciplined study, one can cultivate a deep understanding of the methods and techniques that underlie <em>statistical data handling</em>, and by following, we shall approach data with a rational and objective mindset, illuminating with our analytical skills the meaningful insights and so make more informed decisions.<br> A Stoic would say “Remember, the data is not what you see, but what you make of it. So, approach it with a clear mind, free from <code>bias</code> and preconceptions, and seek the truth that lies hidden within.” By applying oneself to these principles with diligence and perseverance, we may yet unlock the full potential of <em>statistical data handling</em>, and make a valuable contribution to the world of data science.</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/cover_podh.jpg" height="250"></p>
</div></div><ol start="3" type="1">
<li><strong>Probability &amp; Statistics for Engineers and Scientists</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="Walpole2007">(Walpole et al. 2007)</span>, in this tome, a path to comprehension of probability and statistics is laid out before you. It is a journey of discovery that will require patience, diligence, and a willingness to learn. The author presents the tools and techniques needed to analyze data and draw meaningful conclusions. By using R, one can unlock the secrets hidden in the data. Fear not mistakes, for they are but stepping stones towards deeper understanding, only take care to learn from them, and use the knowledge gained to improve your understanding daily. With each chapter, you will gain a greater understanding of the complex and interconnected world of probability and statistics. Embrace the journey, and may the numbers guide you towards enlightenment.</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/cover_orobability_statistics_for_engineers_scientists.jpg" height="250"></p>
</div></div><ol start="4" type="1">
<li><strong>Introduction to Probability and Statistics Using R</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="Kerns2018">(Kerns 2018)</span> recommended by my friend Adam Hyland. It covers the basic concepts of probability and statistics using the <em>R programming language</em>, It is a useful resource for data scientists who wish to gain a deeper understanding of probability and statistics and how to apply them. Starting with basic probability, <code>distributions</code>, <code>hypothesis testing</code>, <code>regression analysis</code>, it then proceeds to more advanced topics such as <code>Bayesian statistics</code>, <code>machine learning</code>, and <code>time series analysis</code>. Each chapter presents clear explanations, examples, and R code to help the reader grasp the theoretical concepts and apply them in practice. By including a wide range of real-world examples and datasets, it helps the readers conect the concepts and techniques with thier application to real data. <a href="https://ipsur.org/">for a free copy</a></li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/cover_introduction_to_probability_and_statistics_using_R.jpg" height="250"></p>
</div></div><ol start="5" type="1">
<li><strong>Statistical Computing with R</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="RizzoMariaL2019ScwR">(Rizzo 2019)</span> is a comprehensive guide to the analysis and manipulation of data using R. Within, we are introduced to a wide variety of statistical concepts and tools that enable us to explore and understand complex datasets. <br> Standard statistical techniques used in data analysis, such as <code>probability</code>, <code>hypothesis testing</code> are covered. We learn about the <code>normal distribution</code> and its importance in statistical analysis, as well as the <code>Poisson distribution</code>, which is used to model counts of events. <br> The book introduces us to the use of <code>statistical transformations</code>, such as the log transformation, which is often used to make skewed data more normal. We also learn about <code>density estimation</code> and the use of histograms and kernel density estimates to visualize data. <br> The concepts of <code>sampling</code> and <code>random variables</code> are explored, as well as the calculation of <code>sample means</code> and <code>standard errors</code>. We also learn about the use of random samples from <code>Monte Carlo simulation</code> to approximate probabilities and calculate statistics. <br> The book covers the use of algorithms and samplers, such as the <code>Metropolis-Hastings</code> algorithm, to explore parameter space and to generate samples from distributions of interest. We learn about the importance of convergence and the use of proposals in Monte Carlo sampling. <br> The concepts of <code>bias</code> and <code>variance</code> are explored, as well as the calculation of <code>confidence intervals</code> and the use of <code>hypothesis testing</code> to evaluate <code>statistical significance</code>. We also learn about the use of the <code>bootstrap</code> and <code>jackknife</code> methods to find the level of uncertainty in our estimates. <br> Throughout the book, we are introduced to the use of R for statistical computing. We learn about the use of formulas to specify statistical models, as well as the use of packages for data manipulation and visualization. <br> Overall, “Statistical Computing with R” is an essential resource for anyone interested in using statistical methods to analyze data. It provides a lucid and comprehensive treatment of statistical concepts and their practical implementation using R.</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/cover_statistical_computing_with_R.jpg" height="250"></p>
</div></div><ol start="6" type="1">
<li><strong>Bayesian methods of Data Analysis</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="carlin2008bayesian">(Carlin and Louis 2008)</span> we are presented with a framework that is grounded in the philosophy of probability theory. We learn to seek a baseline model then approach the problem at hand with a Bayesian perspective. <br> Through the use of <code>Bayesian models</code>, we can compute the <code>conditional distributions</code> of our data and evaluate the error and loss functions. We must consider convergence, the <code>choice of priors</code>, and how they are specified. We use <code>Bayes' rule</code> to compute the <code>posterior distribution</code> and <code>marginal likelihood</code>, and we obtain <code>point estimates</code> and <code>credible intervals</code>. <br> The use of the <code>Gibbs sampler</code> and the <code>Metropolis-Hastings</code> algorithm in <code>MCMC</code> methods are presented as tools to obtain a sample from the posterior distribution. We use <code>WinBUGS</code> code and <code>Monte Carlo</code> simulations to produce results that are in line with the data observed. <br> We are introduced to the concept of the <code>Bayes factor</code>, and how it is used to compare models. We also understand how the use of the <code>Jeffreys prior</code>, the <code>hyperprior</code>, and the <code>conjugate prior</code> can be used to simplify our computations. <br> In Bayesian methods, we use the full conditional distributions to obtain the joint posterior distribution of our parameters. We also compute the marginal posterior distribution, which can be used to obtain a credible interval. <br> We are shown how to deal with univariate and multivariate data, and how to model the <code>random effects</code> and <code>covariate effects</code>. We also understand how to evaluate the performance of our models through <code>histograms</code>, <code>percentiles</code>, and <code>plots</code>. <br> In this work, we are presented with a practical and useful guide to Bayesian methods that can be applied to a variety of problems.</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/cover_bayesian_methods_of_data_analysis.png" height="250"></p>
</div></div><ol start="7" type="1">
<li><a href="https://www.inference.org.uk/itprnn/book.pdf">Information Theory, Inference and Learning Algorithms</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="MacKay2003">(MacKay 2003)</span> by David J.C. MacKay FRS
<ul>
<li><a href="http://videolectures.net/mackay_course_01">Course notes: Information Theory, Pattern Recognition, and Neural Networks</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://www.inference.org.uk/mackay/itprnn/newcover10.gif" height="250"></p>
</div></div><div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BCiZc0n6COY" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-carlin2008bayesian" class="csl-entry">
Carlin, B. P., and T. A. Louis. 2008. <em>Bayesian Methods for Data Analysis</em>. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC Texts in Statistical Science. CRC Press. <a href="https://books.google.co.il/books?id=GTJUt8fcFx8C">https://books.google.co.il/books?id=GTJUt8fcFx8C</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-chambers2008software" class="csl-entry">
Chambers, John M. 2008. <em>Software for Data Analysis Programming with r</em>. New York; London: Springer. <a href="http://www.amazon.de/Software-Data-Analysis-Programming-Statistics/dp/0387759352">http://www.amazon.de/Software-Data-Analysis-Programming-Statistics/dp/0387759352</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-davidson-1996" class="csl-entry">
Davidson, Fred. 1996. <em>Principles of Statistical Data Handling</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4135/9781483348902">https://doi.org/10.4135/9781483348902</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kerns2018" class="csl-entry">
Kerns, G. Jay. 2018. <em>Introduction to Probability and Statistics Using r</em>.
</div>
<div id="ref-MacKay2003" class="csl-entry">
MacKay, David J. C. 2003. <em>Information Theory, Inference, and Learning Algorithms</em>. Copyright Cambridge University Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-RizzoMariaL2019ScwR" class="csl-entry">
Rizzo, Maria L. 2019. <em>Statistical Computing with r Maria l. Rizzo.</em> Second edition. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC the r Series. Boca Raton: CRC Press, Taylor &amp; Francis Group.
</div>
<div id="ref-Walpole2007" class="csl-entry">
Walpole, Ronald E., Raymond H. Myers, Sharon L. Myers, and Keying Ye. 2007. <em>Probability &amp; Statistics for Engineers and Scientists</em>. 8th ed. Upper Saddle River: Pearson Education.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>reading list</category>
  <category>data analysis</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>R programming language</category>
  <category>books</category>
  <category>intelligence</category>
  <category>resolution</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-26-R-books/2011-08-26-R_books.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 05:11:16 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Time management Tips</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-11-time-management/time-management.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-11-time-management/pexels-pixabay-39396.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Pixabay: https://www.pexels.com/photo/clear-glass-with-red-sand-grainer-39396/</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction:</h2>
<p>Effective time management is crucial for success in both personal and professional life. With the right approach, you can achieve more in less time while maintaining a healthy work-life balance. In this article, we’ll explore various time management strategies, focusing on learning from others, project management techniques, and effective meetings. ## Learning from Others To improve your time management skills, consider learning from different sources: 1. <strong>Wisdom from experienced individuals</strong>: Look for insights and advice from people who have been successful in managing their time. They can provide valuable tips and practical approaches to help you make the most of your time. 1. <strong>Fresh perspectives from younger generations</strong>: Younger people often have unique and innovative ideas on how to approach time management. Their perspectives can provide fresh insights on the world and how to navigate it efficiently. 1. <strong>Cassandra’s prophecies</strong>: Although they may seem pessimistic or overly cautious, pay attention to people who predict potential problems or obstacles. By considering their warnings, you can proactively prepare for possible challenges, preventing self-fulfilling prophecies.</p>
</section>
<section id="project-management" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="project-management">Project management</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Measure work by output, not input:</strong> Focus on the results produced rather than the amount of time spent on a task. This will encourage efficiency and productivity.</li>
<li><strong>Define specific goals:</strong> Clearly outline the objectives, responsibilities, and tasks associated with each project or job.</li>
<li><strong>Track goal progress:</strong> Regularly monitor the progress of your goals to ensure they are on track for completion.</li>
<li><strong>Provide periodic progress reports:</strong> Keep stakeholders informed with brief, regular updates on project status.</li>
<li><strong>Set high-quality performance objectives:</strong> Ensure that your goals are challenging, attainable, and aligned with your overall mission.</li>
<li><strong>Maintain a project list:</strong> Keep a running list of all projects, breaking them down into smaller, manageable tasks if necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Focus on the next step, not the final goal:</strong> Concentrate on completing the immediate task at hand rather than getting overwhelmed by the overall project.</li>
<li><strong>Prioritize tasks effectively:</strong> Determine which tasks are most important and tackle them first.</li>
<li><strong>Schedule your day realistically:</strong> Plan your day in a way that allows for adequate time to complete tasks without feeling rushed or overwhelmed.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conducting-efficient-meetings" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conducting-efficient-meetings">Conducting Efficient Meetings:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Establish clear meeting objectives: Ensure that every meeting has a specific purpose, such as group bonding, reaching a group decision, or conducting peer-to-peer negotiations.</li>
<li>Use alternative communication methods when appropriate: Utilize emails and letters for unidirectional information flow or for maintaining records, as they can be more efficient than meetings for certain tasks. ## Conclusion: By implementing these time management strategies, you can increase your productivity, achieve your goals, and maintain a healthy work-life balance. Remember, the key to success is consistently refining and adapting your approach to time management as you encounter new challenges and opportunities.</li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>time management</category>
  <category>productivity</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/blog/posts/2011/2011-08-11-time-management/time-management.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
