<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Oren Bochman&#39;s Blog</title>
<link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Personal website, portfolio and blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>On Learning To Become a Successful Loser</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="on-learning-to-become-a-successful-loser-a-comparison-of-alternative-abstractions-of-learning-processes-in-the-loss-domain" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>On Learning To Become a Successful Loser: A Comparison of Alternative Abstractions of Learning Processes in the Loss Domain</h1>
<p>I tracked this paper due to it being highlighted in <span class="citation" data-cites="Skyrms2010signals">(Skyrms 2010)</span> as the source of a model that learns a signaling systems faster. I got me started with the loss domain. I was eventually able to find how to speed up learning by in the Lewis signaling game by considering the much more likely mistakes. Once I got on this algorithm I was thinking that using this idea for Bayesian updating of beliefs. This eventually led me to a second algorithm that was able to rapidly adjust a belief regarding the the state of the world in lewis signaling game with changing distributions.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Skyrms2010signals" class="csl-entry">
Skyrms, Brian. 2010. <span>“<span class="nocase">Signals: Evolution, Learning, and Information</span>.”</span> In. Oxford University Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199580828.003.0013">https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199580828.003.0013</a>.
</div></div><div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="../../../images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="On Learning to become a successful loser in a nutshell"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="On Learning to become a successful loser in a nutshell"></a></p>
<figcaption>On Learning to become a successful loser in a nutshell</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Besides having this amazing title this research paper compares five mathematical models that predict student behavior in repeated decision-making tasks involving gains and losses. <mark>The core issue is how to accurately represent the effect of losses on learning, as observed deviations from expected utility theory exist</mark> They conducted an experiment and find that learning in the loss domain can be faster than in the gain domain. <mark>The main results suggest that adding a constant to the payoff matrix can accelerate the learning process</mark>, supporting the adjustable reference point (ARP) abstraction of the effect of losses proposed by <span class="citation" data-cites="Roth1995Learning">(Roth and Erev 1995)</span>.</p>
<audio controls="1">
<source src="podcast.mp3" data-external="1" type="audio/mpeg">

</audio>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>One of the main difficulties in the development of descriptive models of learning in repeated choice tasks involves the abstraction of the effect of losses. The present paper explains this difficulty, summarizes its common solutions, and presents an experiment that was designed to compare the descriptive power of the specific quantifications of these solutions proposed in recent research. The experiment utilized a probability learning task. In each of the experiment’s 500 trials participants were asked to predict the appearance of one of two colors. The probabilities of appearance of the colors were different but fixed during the entire experiment. The experimental manipulation involved an addition of a constant to the payoffs. The results demonstrate that learning in the loss domain can be faster than learning in the gain domain; adding a constant to the payoff matrix can affect the learning process. These results are consistent with by <span class="citation" data-cites="Roth1995Learning">(Roth and Erev 1995)</span> adjustable reference point abstraction of the effect of losses, and violate all other models</p>
<p>— <span class="citation" data-cites="bereby1998learning">(Bereby-Meyer and Erev 1998)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Roth1995Learning" class="csl-entry">
Roth, Alvin, and Ido Erev. 1995. <span>“Learning in Extensive-Form Games: Experimental Data and Simple Dynamic Models in the Intermediate Term.”</span> <em>Games and Economic Behavior</em> 8 (1): 164–212. <a href="https://EconPapers.repec.org/RePEc:eee:gamebe:v:8:y:1995:i:1:p:164-212">https://EconPapers.repec.org/RePEc:eee:gamebe:v:8:y:1995:i:1:p:164-212</a>.
</div><div id="ref-bereby1998learning" class="csl-entry">
Bereby-Meyer, Yoella, and Ido Erev. 1998. <span>“On Learning to Become a Successful Loser: A Comparison of Alternative Abstractions of Learning Processes in the Loss Domain.”</span> <em>Journal of Mathematical Psychology</em> 42 (2-3): 266–86.
</div></div></div>
</section>
<section id="outline" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="outline">Outline:</h2>
<section id="introduction" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<ul>
<li>Highlights the difficulty in developing descriptive models of learning in repeated choice tasks that involve potential losses.</li>
<li>Presents the main goal of the paper: to compare the descriptive power of five distinct solutions to this difficulty and to identify a robust approximation of learning in simple decision tasks.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-challenge-and-alternative-solutions" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenge-and-alternative-solutions">The Challenge and Alternative Solutions</h3>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="table-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Models and Solutions"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/table-01.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Models and Solutions"></a></p>
<figcaption>Models and Solutions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div><ul>
<li>Discusses the difficulty in abstracting the effect of losses given the approximately linear relationship between choice probabilities and the ratio of accumulated payoffs observed in the gain domain.</li>
<li>Introduces probability learning tasks used to derive and compare the predictions of different models.</li>
<li>Presents five alternative solutions to the problem:
<ul>
<li>Low Reference Point (LRP):
<ul>
<li>Transforms objective payoffs into non-negative rewards by subtracting the worst possible outcome</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Adjustable Reference Point and Truncation (ARP)
<ul>
<li>Uses an evolving reference point to distinguish gains and losses and truncates negative values to ensure positive propensities</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Exponential Response Rule (EDS, EFP, EWA)
<ul>
<li>Applies an exponential function to propensities, eliminating the need for handling negative values directly. Examples include Exponential Discounted Sum (EDS), Exponential Fictitious Play (EFP), and Experience Weighted Attractions (EWA) models</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Cumulative Normal Response Rule (CNFP)
<ul>
<li>Uses a cumulative normal distribution to model the relationship between payoffs and propensities- Employs the cumulative normal distribution function to map propensities (which can be negative) to choice probabilities (which are always between 0 and 1). The CNFP model exemplifies this.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Relative Reinforcement solutions (CLO)
<ul>
<li>Uses outcome-specific parameters to determine the impact of different outcomes on choice probabilities. The Cardinal Linear Operator (CLO) model demonstrates this.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Describes the specific implementations of these solutions through different models, including their assumptions and parameterizations.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="experiment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="experiment">Experiment</h3>
<ul>
<li>Describes the experimental method, including the participants, the procedure, and the payoff structure of the probability learning task across three conditions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="results" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results">Results</h3>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="table-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Models and Solutions"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/table-01.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Models and Solutions"></a></p>
<figcaption>Models and Solutions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div><ul>
<li>Presents the aggregated experimental results, showing a significant effect of the reward condition on the proportion of optimal choices.</li>
<li>Compares the quantitative predictive and descriptive power of the models using correlation and mean squared deviation (MSD) measures.</li>
<li>Discusses the between-subject variability observed in the data and the limitations of the models in capturing this variability.</li>
<li>Conducts a model-based analysis to evaluate the robustness of the condition effect.</li>
<li>Performs a sensitivity analysis to assess the robustness of the ARP model’s predictions to changes in parameter values.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h3>
<ul>
<li>Discusses the main finding that the addition of constants to payoffs affects the speed of learning, highlighting the role of the distinction between gains and losses.</li>
<li>Notes the advantage of the ARP model in capturing the observed results and acknowledges the potential validity of other solutions under specific assumptions or parameterizations.</li>
<li>Addresses the generality of the findings by discussing:
<ul>
<li>Settings where the ARP model’s predictions are consistent with previous research (probability learning, signal detection).</li>
<li>Settings where the model might fail (learning among only positive outcomes, influence of other players’ payoffs).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions">Conclusions</h3>
<ul>
<li>Concludes that human learning is affected by the distinction between gains and losses.</li>
<li>Emphasizes that modeling this distinction, particularly through the adjustable reference point approach, improves the descriptive power of adaptive learning models.</li>
<li>Acknowledges the need for further research to refine the quantification of the reference point for a more accurate and generalizable model.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="key-takeaways" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>
<ul>
<li>In most RL settings rewards are sparse. One way to speed up learning is to try and increase our reward signal.</li>
<li>This is the basis for seeling out to decompose the reward signal into an internal motivation for the agent and an external motivation for the problem designer.</li>
<li>Another approach though is to consider the loss domain. If we can get signals out of losses we can speed up learning and RL agents are slow learners - especially deep RL agents.</li>
<li>A third approach that I was able to make use of is to use both the loss domain and the gain domain to update beliefs about the possible states of the world. This was allowed me to speed up Bayesian learning algorithm for a coordination task.</li>
</ul>
<p>Besides this the paper has a lot of possible options for potential update rules to get this potential speed up.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How does adding a constant to all payoffs in a decision task affect learning, and which model best explains this effect?</li>
</ol>
<p>One of the results I learned is that adding a constant to the payoff matrix doesn’t change it. In fact linear transformations of the payoff matrix don’t change the outcomes. In policy gradient methods this we call this trick learning with baselines. What we see is that it doesn’t bias the estimator but can drastically reduce the variance of the estimator. And this variance is the noise that slows down learning by the agent. So adding a constant can surprisingly impact learning speed. The ARP model uniquely predicts this: subtracting a constant to introduce losses speeds learning compared to a purely gain-based scenario. This highlights the psychological impact of the gain-loss framing.</p>
<p>Another insight I had about this is while trying to abstract the RL algorithms. Was that under some conditions we can convert the reward function into a distance metric. Having a metric makes navigation states space much simpler. I really can’t think of a better feature.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>What are the limitations of the ARP model?</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The ARP model, with its current parameters, assumes an initial reference point of zero and a slow adjustment process. This might not hold when:
<ul>
<li>All options are positive: The model would predict slow learning even when clear differences exist.</li>
<li>Social comparison exists: People may adjust their reference point based on other players’ payoffs, a factor not currently incorporated in the model.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>How would you define the loss domain and the gain domain ?</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><p>The gain domain is when choice probabilities are approximately linearly related to the ratio of accumulated reinforcement.</p></li>
<li><p>The loss domain is when negative payoffs are possible.</p></li>
<li><p>In the gain domain, the probabilities of choosing an alternative match the ratio of accumulated reinforcement, meaning that individuals are more likely to choose options that have yielded higher rewards in the past.</p></li>
<li><p>Descriptive models have to assume that choice probabilities are determined by a function of the accumulated reinforcements, which must have strictly positive values. However, this presents a problem when losses are possible because negative payoffs can result in negative values for the function.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>In the paper the autors mention the value function from prospect theory c.f. <span class="citation" data-cites="kahneman1979econ">(Kahneman 1979)</span>. How does this relate to the ARP model?</li>
</ol>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-kahneman1979econ" class="csl-entry">
Kahneman, Daniel. 1979. <span>“Econ Ometrica i Ci.”</span> <em>Econometrica</em> 47 (2): 263–91.
</div></div><p>The authors state that models that use solutions other than the adjustable reference point can account for the results of the study under the assumption that the model’s parameters can be affected by the payoffs. One way to account for this is to use reinforcement functions with the characteristics of Prospect Theory’s value function. Prospect theory, developed by Kahneman and Tversky, suggests that individuals make decisions based on the potential value of losses and gains rather than the final outcome, and that losses have a greater impact on individuals than gains do. This relates to the ARP model because it also assumes that reinforcements are evaluated relative to a reference point, meaning outcomes above the reference point are perceived as gains (reinforcements) and outcomes below the reference point are perceived as losses (punishments).</p>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>Is there a formal definition of this prospect theoretic value function?</li>
</ol>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="value-function.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="a value function"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/value-function.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="a value function"></a></p>
<figcaption>a value function</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div><p>A key element of this theory is the value function, which exhibits these characteristics: - It’s defined on deviations from a reference point. - It’s generally concave for gains and convex for losses. - It’s steeper for losses than for gains, meaning an equivalent loss has a greater psychological impact than the corresponding gain.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The Paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>
</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2025,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {On {Learning} {To} {Become} a {Successful} {Loser}},
  date = {2025-01-02},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2025. <span>“On Learning To Become a Successful
Loser.”</span> January 2, 2025. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>RL</category>
  <category>Reinforcement Learning</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1998/becoming-a-successful-loser/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Emergence of Linguistic Communication from Referential Games with Symbolic and Pixel Input</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2018/Lazaridou2018Emergence/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fig-iclr-2018" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-iclr-2018-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<iframe src="https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?height=300&amp;href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Ficlr.cc%2Fvideos%2F2125495797479475%2F&amp;show_text=false&amp;width=500&amp;t=4701" width="500" height="300" style="border:none;overflow:hidden" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; picture-in-picture; web-share">
</iframe>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-iclr-2018-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: ICLR Presentation by Angeliki Lazaridou on Emergence of Linguistic Communication from Referential Games with Symbolic and Pixel Input
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div><div id="fig-iclr-2018" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-iclr-2018-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GnBdK61cBUY" title="DeepMind" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-iclr-2018-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: Talk by Hugh Perkins on this paper Titled “DeepMind’s emergent communication using pixel input”
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div><div id="fig-towards-multi-agent-emergent-communications" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-towards-multi-agent-emergent-communications-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FgN01DCHfjU" title="Towards Multi-agent Emergent Communication | Angeliki Lazaridou " frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-towards-multi-agent-emergent-communications-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: Talk titled ‘Towards Multi-agent Emergent Communication’ by Angeliki Lazaridou at Imperial College London in the ICARL Seminar Series - 2022 Spring
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>

<p>This is the paper that Marco Baroni used to explain the emergence of languages in his talk “Is Composonality over rated?”.</p>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="lazaridou2018emergence">(Lazaridou et al. 2018)</span> the authors look emergence of language using a deep reinforcement learning approach. They train reinforcement-learning neural network agents on referential communication games. They extend previous work, in which agents were trained in symbolic environments, by developing agents which are able to learn from raw pixel data, a more challenging and realistic input representation. They find that the degree of structure found in the input data affects the nature of the emerged protocols, and thereby corroborate the hypothesis that structured compositional language is most likely to emerge when agents perceive the world as being structured.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR: Emergence of Linguistic Communication from Referential Games with Symbolic and Pixel Input
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="../../../images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Emergence of Linguistic Communication in a nutshell"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Emergence of Linguistic Communication in a nutshell"></a></p>
<figcaption>Emergence of Linguistic Communication in a nutshell</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The goal of the paper is <mark>to investigate the properties of communication protocols that emerge when reinforcement learning agents are trained on referential communication games</mark>. The study aims to explore how agents learn to communicate in scenarios with structured and disentangled input data, as well as in more challenging scenarios with raw pixel input, resembling the complexity of real-world environments.</p>
<p>The training of agents just described was successful and the researchers found that <mark>agents can produce structured and compositional communication protocols when presented with disentangled inputs, but <strong>struggle to do so when presented with entangled raw pixel input</strong></mark>. The emergent protocols were found to be <strong>unstable</strong> and highly grounded in the specific game situation, leading to specialized ad-hoc naming conventions.</p>
<audio controls="1">
<source src="podcast.mp3" data-external="1" type="audio/mpeg">

</audio>
</div>
</div>
<section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The ability of algorithms to evolve or learn (compositional) communication protocols has traditionally been studied in the language evolution literature through the use of emergent communication tasks. Here we scale up this research by us ing contemporary deep learning methods and by training reinforcement-learning neural network agents on referential communication games. We extend previous work, in which agents were trained in symbolic environments, by developing agents which are able to learn from raw pixel data, a more challenging and realistic input representation. We find that the degree of structure found in the input data affects the nature of the emerged protocols, and thereby corroborate the hypothesis that structured compositional language is most likely to emerge when agents perceive the world as being structured</p>
<p>— <span class="citation" data-cites="lazaridou2018emergence">(Lazaridou et al. 2018)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-lazaridou2018emergence" class="csl-entry">
Lazaridou, Angeliki, Karl Moritz Hermann, Karl Tuyls, and Stephen Clark. 2018. <span>“Emergence of Linguistic Communication from Referential Games with Symbolic and Pixel Input.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.03984">https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.03984</a>.
</div></div></div>
</section>
<section id="outline" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="outline">Outline</h2>
<p>So I went through the paper and outlined most of the methodolgy etc. Its a bit long but I think it is worth it. Here is a quick outline. I might come back and add more material later. But I think the video above though not dierectly on this paper is a good explainer to understand this more easily.</p>
<section id="introduction" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<ul>
<li>Explores the emergence of linguistic communication through referential games with symbolic and pixel inputs.</li>
<li>Motivated by understanding the role of environmental conditions on emergent communication.</li>
<li>Introduces the use of deep reinforcement learning agents to scale up traditional studies of language emergence.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="referential-games-framework" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="referential-games-framework">Referential Games Framework</h3>
<ul>
<li>Based on multi-agent cooperative reinforcement learning, inspired by the Lewis signaling game.</li>
<li>Involves a speaker communicating a target object to a listener, who identifies it among distractors.</li>
<li>Differentiates between symbolic data (structured and disentangled) and pixel data (entangled).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="study-1-referential-game-with-symbolic-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="study-1-referential-game-with-symbolic-data">Study 1: Referential Game with Symbolic Data</h3>
<ul>
<li>Uses disentangled input from the Visual Attributes for Concepts Dataset.</li>
<li>Demonstrates that agents can learn compositional protocols when input is structured.</li>
<li>Explores the effects of message length, showing improved communicative success and reduced ambiguity with longer messages.</li>
<li>Investigates how context-dependent distractors impact language emergence and object confusability.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="study-2-referential-game-with-raw-pixel-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="study-2-referential-game-with-raw-pixel-data">Study 2: Referential Game with Raw Pixel Data</h3>
<ul>
<li>Employs synthetic scenes of geometric objects generated using the MuJoCo engine.</li>
<li>Agents learn to process raw pixel input without pre-training, achieving significant communicative success.</li>
<li>Highlights environmental pressures’ role in shaping emergent protocols, leading to overfitting and ad-hoc conventions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="structural-properties-of-emergent-protocols" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="structural-properties-of-emergent-protocols">Structural Properties of Emergent Protocols</h3>
<ul>
<li>Examines the topographic similarity metric, correlating object similarity with message similarity.</li>
<li>Observes compositional signals in structured environments but instability and environmental overfitting with pixel input.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="probe-models" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="probe-models">Probe Models</h3>
<ul>
<li>Analyzes the speaker’s visual representations using linear classifiers.</li>
<li>Finds that disentanglement is necessary for encoding object properties and effective communication.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<ul>
<li>Demonstrates that structured input aids compositionality, while raw pixel input challenges protocol stability.</li>
<li>Highlights the scalability of emergent communication studies with realistic data and deep learning techniques.</li>
<li>Suggests future work to mitigate overfitting and promote generalization across diverse environments.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="comments" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comments">Comments</h2>
<p>What are the main research questions of the paper?</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How do environmental or pre-linguistic conditions affect the nature of the communication protocol that an agent learns?</li>
<li>Can reinforcement learning agents successfully communicate when presented with raw pixel input, in addition to symbolic and highly structured input data?</li>
<li>How does the degree of structure in input data influence the nature of emergent communication protocols, particularly concerning the hypothesis that structured compositional language emerges when agents perceive the world as structured?</li>
</ol>
<p>Looking over this paper I did not see any outrageous claims not much that I thought wrong. Although Lazaridou has a number of criticism on research in this area this paper seems sound work.</p>
<section id="the-referential-game" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-referential-game">The referential game</h3>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fig-01" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-01-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="p3-referntial-game.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="The referential game"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2018/Lazaridou2018Emergence/p3-referntial-game.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
<figcaption>The referential game</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>First, a speaker is presented with a target object (highlighted as CAR in the symbolic example on the left, and highlighted as the far right im- age in the pixel example on the right). Then, by making use of an alphabet consisting of primitive discrete symbols (“22”, “10”, “0”,“2”), the speaker constructs a message describing that object (“22 2 0”). <strong>We will refer to the set of all distinct messages generated by the speaker as their lexicon or protocol</strong>. Finally, the listener is presented with the target and a set of destructor objects, and—by making use of the speaker’s message—has to identify the target object from the set of candidate objects. Communicative success is defined as the correct identification of the target by the listening agent</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig quarto-uncaptioned" id="fig-01-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div><p>Although the referential game isn’t a novelty and the authors give a number of prior works that use it, I do suspect that using the referential game has some possible pitfalls. Let’s consider for a second how the referential game differs from the vanilla Lewis Signaling game and if these differences should be significant.</p>
<p>In a vanilla Lewis signaling game the sender encodes the pre-linguistic object into a message and the receiver has to pick one state from all states. In this game a good sender should be able to pick a unique message per state (assuming there are sufficient<sup>1</sup> signals and it does not make use of homonyms).</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;for a simple system one per state is enough. For complex signaling systems this depends on how the atomic signals are aggreaged into complex ones. If the are assembled with replacement into a sequence of length k there are <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%7CS%7C%5Ek"> complex symbols possible. If additional structure is imposed there may be less possible states. If partial sequences are allowed we may have almost twice as many states.</p></div></div><p>The receiver needs to match the signal with a state. It can pick one from the undecoded states. This is initially a task with en expectation of 1/|S|. Once it solves a messages it should eliminate its states thus increase its expectation of success.</p>
<p>In the referential games I abstract to a two round extensive form game. In the first round the sender and receiver play a classification game. Sender looks at the pre-linguistic object and classifies it. It then encodes it into a sequence of symbols. The encoder has an error rate and should perform poorly as it has no pretraining.</p>
<p>In the referential game we can imagine two rounds. In the first round the agent</p>
<p>Let’s assume that the sender encodes each input into a unique message or at least unique up to</p>
<p>If there are S states the</p>
<p>In the referential game the receiver need to solve a multiple choice question with one answer and several distractors by decoding the message from the sender.</p>
<p>The researchers call the language that emerges a lexicon or a protocol rather than a language or a signaling system.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>To call it a lexicon is tantamount to admitting there is no grammar and that the agents are using a simple lewis signaling game. One in which they coordinate a single symbol with each pre-linguistic item or class.</li>
</ol>
<p>A complex signaling system</p>
<p>One term I don’t know if i like is pre-linguistic concepts, usually we call this as the states. However I think that this term isn’t bad at all. It suggests that we arn’t looking just at states but at an item we want to talk about. This makes more sense particularly when we think about bitmaps of states - they are less like states.</p>
<p>One more point is that by adding the vision learning we are adding a second game. Call it a classification game. The agent needs to succeed at classification game otherwise they are just guessing. It worth while to consider though that just guessing with a good memory is enough to develop a signaling system.</p>
<p>There is a massive asymmetry between the sender and the receiver that is not extant in the original game. The sender can learn all images via a ground truth while the receiver can only learn about the correct ones.</p>
<p>So that as a framing game this needs to be reconsidered. What I mean is that the sender’s vision should be evaluated compared in a scale between an agent with a perfect vision and perfect blindness as baselines. And the same for receiver.</p>
<p>The vision capability should be factored in to the evaluation of the agent’s learning of the signaling system.</p>
<p>The paper does have many interesting ideas and shows methods, for achieving them. In a number of areas I think one could do better, but I doubt the results should be very different.</p>
<p>One area that seems wort further investigation is CONCEPTUAL ALIGNMENT in appendix A. This seems to be related to semantic grounding — getting the agents language concepts/semantics to align with the world or with a second set of semantics like say a human language.</p>
<p>What they consider here is much more specific - does the visual capacity learned by the agents provide them with a disentangled view of the world that is in line with the compositional structure of the state space they are observing (called pre-linguistic concepts).</p>
<p>It seems that either the methodology is inadequate or that there is a problem with alignment.</p>
<p>What might be done -</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>consider a hierarchial model that learns just this types of relationship.</li>
<li>think more on this comparing the vision capabilities of the agent is truly fascinating.</li>
<li>It seems the crux of the matter is if the softmax layers diverge for classifying the atomic concepts and the compositional concepts?</li>
</ol>
<p>If they do we might consider that the agents vision are not seeing things in the same way. But consider that the sender always knows the state the receivers might not know the state most of the time. So thier vision might be less developed</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Emergence of Linguistic communication"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>Emergence of Linguistic communication</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2025,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Emergence of {Linguistic} {Communication} from {Referential}
    {Games} with {Symbolic} and {Pixel} {Input}},
  date = {2025-01-01},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2018/Lazaridou2018Emergence/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2025. <span>“Emergence of Linguistic Communication from
Referential Games with Symbolic and Pixel Input.”</span> January 1,
2025. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2018/Lazaridou2018Emergence/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2018/Lazaridou2018Emergence/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>review</category>
  <category>compositionality</category>
  <category>neural networks</category>
  <category>signaling systems</category>
  <category>language evolution</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2018/Lazaridou2018Emergence/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2018/Lazaridou2018Emergence/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Linguistic generalization and compositionality in modern artificial neural networks</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2019/baroni-linguistic-generalization/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="../../../images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Linguistic generalization and compositionality in a nutshell"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Linguistic generalization and compositionality in a nutshell"></a></p>
<figcaption>Linguistic generalization and compositionality in a nutshell</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="baroni2020linguistic">(Baroni 2020)</span> the author discusses the role of deep artificial neural networks in natural language processing tasks and their generalization abilities. The paper reviews the innovations characterizing modern deep language processing networks, such as large training datasets, gated recurrent networks, encoder-decoder architectures, and attention mechanisms. It then delves into studies examining the generalization abilities of deep networks, particularly in the context of grammatical generalization and compositional tasks. The paper presents empirical evidence suggesting that deep networks are capable of subtle grammar-dependent generalizations but do not rely on systematic compositional rules. It discusses the implications of these findings for linguistics and cognitive science, highlighting the need for better analytical tools to understand the mechanisms underlying the intriguing behavior of deep networks in language processing tasks.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><section id="abstract" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In the last decade, deep artificial neural networks have achieved astounding performance in many natural language processing tasks. Given the high productivity of language, these models must possess effective generalization abilities. It is widely assumed that humans handle linguistic productivity by means of algebraic compositional rules: Are deep networks similarly compositional? After reviewing the main innovations characterizing current deep language processing networks, I discuss a set of studies suggesting that deep networks are capable of subtle grammar dependent generalizations, but also that they do not rely on systematic compositional rules. I argue that the intriguing behavior of these devices (still awaiting a full understanding) should be of interest to linguists and cognitive scientists, as it offers a new perspective on possible computational strategies to deal with linguistic productivity beyond rule-based compositionality, and it might lead to new insights into the less systematic generalization patterns that also appear in natural language.</p>
<p>— <span class="citation" data-cites="baroni2020linguistic">(Baroni 2020)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-baroni2020linguistic" class="csl-entry">
Baroni, Marco. 2020. <span>“Linguistic Generalization and Compositionality in Modern Artificial Neural Networks.”</span> <em>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B</em> 375 (1791): 20190307.
</div></div></div>
</section>
<section id="introduction" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">1. Introduction</h3>
<ul>
<li>Mentions the history of neural networks as tools for modeling cognitive phenomena and their recent success as machine learning algorithms, particularly in natural language processing.</li>
<li>Highlights the need to understand how neural networks achieve their language skills, given their impressive performance in tasks such as machine translation.</li>
<li>Presents the argument for studying deep networks from a comparative psychology perspective, to gain insights into the nature of linguistic tasks and how computational devices solve them.</li>
<li>Discusses the concept of linguistic productivity, its relation to compositionality, and the debate on whether neural networks possess this ability, focusing on the intriguing generalization patterns observed in deep networks.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="modern-deep-networks-for-language-processing-what-has-changed" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modern-deep-networks-for-language-processing-what-has-changed">2. Modern Deep Networks for Language Processing: What Has Changed</h3>
<ul>
<li>Discusses the role of large training datasets in enhancing neural network performance, enabling complex, multi-layer architecture training, and facilitating language modeling as a general-purpose approach.</li>
<li>Describes gated recurrent networks, such as LSTMs and GRUs, with their information flow regulation mechanisms (gates) enhancing control and performance.</li>
<li>Explains the innovation of encoder-decoder architectures, decoupling input and output processing for effective handling of sequence-to-sequence tasks, commonly used in machine translation.</li>
<li>Presents the concept of attention mechanisms, enabling dynamic information access from past states, further improving the performance of encoder-decoder architectures, particularly in models relying heavily on attention over recurrent connections.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="colorless-green-grammatical-generalization-in-deep-networks" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="colorless-green-grammatical-generalization-in-deep-networks">3. Colorless Green Grammatical Generalization in Deep Networks</h3>
<ul>
<li>Discusses the generalization abilities of modern language-processing neural networks, particularly in the context of machine translation, and the ongoing research into understanding the basis of this performance (shallow heuristics vs.&nbsp;grammar-based generalizations).</li>
<li>Presents Gulordava et al.’s study testing grammatical generalization in recurrent networks using controlled, nonsensical sentences designed to assess long-distance number agreement, showing above-chance performance across multiple languages.</li>
<li>Highlights Lakretz et al.’s ablation and connectivity studies of the Gulordava network, revealing specialized units sensitive to long-distance number information and connected to sub-networks sensitive to syntactic constituency, suggesting genuine grammatical processing mechanisms.</li>
<li>Notes that while networks demonstrate grammatical productivity in these studies, further research is needed to determine if they possess a rule-based system akin to traditional linguistic theory.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="compositional-generalization-can-deep-networks-dax-twice" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compositional-generalization-can-deep-networks-dax-twice">4. Compositional Generalization: Can Deep Networks Dax Twice?</h3>
<ul>
<li>Introduces the SCAN benchmark, a miniature language designed to test compositional abilities in sequence-processing networks, where networks learn to map commands to action sequences.</li>
<li>Explains the random split in SCAN, testing generic productivity, and the jump split, testing systematic compositionality by introducing a novel verb (“jump”) only in isolation during training and evaluating its use in composite commands during testing.</li>
<li>Describes the around-right split, controlling for distributional biases in the jump split, where networks are trained on commands excluding the combination of “around” and “right” but with sufficient evidence of their individual behavior.</li>
<li>Presents results showing recurrent networks excel in the random split but fail in the jump and around-right splits, while a convolutional network with heavy attention achieves partial success, suggesting a non-systematic form of generalization.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">5. Conclusion</h3>
<ul>
<li>Summarizes the surprising empirical evidence suggesting modern deep networks are proficient in language processing without demonstrably possessing compositional rules.</li>
<li>Discusses the need for better analytical tools to understand the mechanisms underlying this dissociation between productive grammatical competence and systematic compositionality.</li>
<li>Highlights the importance of exploring whether enhancing compositionality in neural networks can lead to improved adaptability and learning speed, potentially addressing their current limitations in tasks like machine reading and natural language inference.</li>
<li>Notes the potential for comparative studies between neural networks and human language, offering insights into the less systematic and fuzzy aspects of linguistic productivity, ultimately contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of human language.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Linguistic generalization and compositionality in modern artificial neural networks"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>Linguistic generalization and compositionality in modern artificial neural networks</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2025,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Linguistic Generalization and Compositionality in Modern
    Artificial Neural Networks},
  date = {2025-01-01},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2019/baroni-linguistic-generalization/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2025. <span>“Linguistic Generalization and
Compositionality in Modern Artificial Neural Networks.”</span> January
1, 2025. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2019/baroni-linguistic-generalization/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2019/baroni-linguistic-generalization/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>review, compositionality neural networks signaling systems language evolution</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2019/baroni-linguistic-generalization/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2019/baroni-linguistic-generalization/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Compositionality and Generalization in Emergent Languages</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/compositionality-and-generalization/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="review-of-compositionality-and-generalization-in-emergent-languages" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review-of-compositionality-and-generalization-in-emergent-languages">Review of “Compositionality and Generalization in Emergent Languages”</h2>
<p>Very exciting - this is a paper with a lot of interesting ideas. It comes with a a lot of code in the form of a library called EGG as well as many JuPyteR notebooks. There is also a video of the talk at NeurIPS 2020.</p>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="chaabouni-etal-2020-compositionality">(Chaabouni et al. 2020)</span> the authors look at ideas from representation learning and apply them to emergent languages in deep networks. THey come up with a number of results.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Natural language allows us to refer to novel composite concepts by combining expressions denoting their parts according to systematic rules, a property known as compositionality. In this paper, we study whether the language emerging in deep multi-agent simulations possesses a similar ability to refer to novel primitive combinations, and whether it accomplishes this feat by strategies akin to human-language compositionality. Equipped with new ways to measure compositionality in emergent languages <mark>inspired by disentanglement in representation learning</mark>, we establish three main results.</p>
<p>First, <mark>given sufficiently large input spaces, the emergent language will naturally develop the ability to refer to novel composite concepts.</mark></p>
<p>Second, there is <mark>no correlation between the degree of compositionality of an emergent language and its ability to generalize</mark>.</p>
<p>Third, <mark>while compositionality is not necessary for generalization, it provides an advantage in terms of language transmission</mark>: The more compositional a language is, the more easily it will be picked up by new learners, even when the latter differ in architecture from the original agents. We conclude that compositionality does not arise from simple generalization pressure, but if an emergent language does chance upon it, it will be more likely to survive and thrive</p>
<p>— <span class="citation" data-cites="chaabouni-etal-2020-compositionality">(Chaabouni et al. 2020)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></div>
</section>
<section id="outline" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="outline">Outline</h2>
<p>Here is the outline of the paper:</p>
<section id="introduction" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<ul>
<li>Describes a variant of Lewis signaling game used to study the emergence of reference to composite concepts in deep multi-agent simulations.</li>
<li>Discusses two specific and intuitive compositionality strategies that capture common compositional structures in natural languages.<br>
</li>
<li>Introduces two new compositionality measures, positional disentanglement (posdis) and bag-of-symbols disentanglement (bosdis), inspired by work on disentanglement in representation learning.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="measurements" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measurements">Measurements</h3>
<ul>
<li>Describes the commonly used <strong>topographic similarity</strong> (topsim) metric.</li>
<li>Introduces and defines two new measures of compositionality:
<ul>
<li>posdis - <strong>positional disentanglement</strong> and</li>
<li>bosdis - <strong>bag-of-symbols disentanglement</strong>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Explains how the new measures are similar to the <strong>Information Gap disentanglement measure</strong> used in representation learning.</li>
<li>Illustrates the behavior of the three compositionality metrics on three miniature languages in the Appendix.</li>
</ul>
<div id="note-topsim" class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Topographic Similarity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Given these two lists, the topographic similarity is defined as their negative Spearman ρ correlation (since we are correlating distances with similarities, negative values of correlation indicate topographic similarity of the two spaces). <mark>Intuitively, if similar objects share much of the message structure (e.g., common prefixes or suffixes), and dissimilar objects have little common structure in their respective messages, then the topographic similarity should be high</mark>, the highest possible value being 1 – <span class="citation" data-cites="lazaridou2018emergence">(Lazaridou et al. 2018)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cmathit%7Btopsim%7D=%5Crho%5Cleft(%5Cleft%5C%7Bd%5Cleft(%5Cmathbf%7Bx%7D%5E%7B(i)%7D,%20%5Cmathbf%7Bx%7D%5E%7B(j)%7D%5Cright),%20d%5Cleft(%5Cmathbf%7Bm%7D%5E%7B(i)%7D,%20%5Cmathbf%7Bm%7D%5E%7B(j)%7D%5Cright)%5Cright%5C%7D_%7Bi,%20j=1%7D%5E%7Bn%7D%5Cright)%0A"></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-lazaridou2018emergence" class="csl-entry">
Lazaridou, Angeliki, Karl Moritz Hermann, Karl Tuyls, and Stephen Clark. 2018. <span>“Emergence of Linguistic Communication from Referential Games with Symbolic and Pixel Input.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.03984">https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.03984</a>.
</div></div><div id="note-posdis" class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Positional Disentanglement
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>positional disentanglement</strong> (posdis) metric measures whether symbols in specific positions tend to univocally refer to the values of a specific attribute. This order-dependent strategy is commonly encountered in natural language structures (and it is a pre-condition for sophisticated syntactic structures to emerge) – <span class="citation" data-cites="chaabouni-etal-2020-compositionality">(Chaabouni et al. 2020)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cmathit%7Bposdis%7D=%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bc_%7Blen%7D%7D%20%5Csum_%7Bj=1%7D%5E%7Bc_%7Blen%7D%7D%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cmathcal%7BI%7D(s_j,a%5Ej_1)-%5Cmathcal%7BI%7D(s_j,a%5Ej_2)%7D%7B%5Cmathcal%7BH%7D(s_j)%7D%0A"></p>
<ul>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_j"> the j<sup>th</sup> symbol of a message and</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a%5Ej_1"> the attribute that has the highest mutual information with <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_j%20:%20a%5Ej_1%20=%20arg%20max_a%20%5Cmathcal%7BI%7D(s_j%20;%20a)"></li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a%5Ej_2"> the attribute that has the second highest mutual information with <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_j%20:%20a%5Ej_2%20=%20arg%20max_%7Ba%20%5Cneq%20a%5Ej_1%7D%20%5Cmathcal%7BI%7D(s_j%20;%20a)"></li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmathcal%7BH%7D(s_j)"> the entropy of j-th position (used as a normalizing term)</li>
</ul>
<p>positions with zero entropy are ignored in the computation.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><div id="note-bosdis" class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Bag-of-symbols Disentanglement
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Posdis assumes that a language uses positional information to disambiguate symbols. However, we can easily imagine a language where symbols univocally refer to distinct input elements independently of where they occur, making order irrelevant.3 Hence, we also introduce <strong>bag-of-symbols disentanglement</strong> (bosdis). The latter maintains the requirement for symbols to univocally refer to distinct meanings, but captures the intuition of a permutation-invariant language, where only symbol counts are informative – <span class="citation" data-cites="chaabouni-etal-2020-compositionality">(Chaabouni et al. 2020)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cmathit%7Bbodis%7D=%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bc_%7Bvoc%7D%7D%20%5Csum_%7Bj=1%7D%5E%7Bc_%7Bvoc%7D%7D%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cmathcal%7BI%7D(n_j,a%5Ej_1)-%5Cmathcal%7BI%7D(n_j,a%5Ej_2)%7D%7B%5Cmathcal%7BH%7D(n_j)%7D%0A"></p>
<ul>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n_j"> a counter of the j-th symbol in a message</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-chaabouni-etal-2020-compositionality" class="csl-entry">
Chaabouni, Rahma, Eugene Kharitonov, Diane Bouchacourt, Emmanuel Dupoux, and Marco Baroni. 2020. <span>“Compositionality and Generalization in Emergent Languages.”</span> In <em>Proceedings of the 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</em>, edited by Dan Jurafsky, Joyce Chai, Natalie Schluter, and Joel Tetreault, 4427–42. Online: Association for Computational Linguistics. <a href="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.acl-main.407">https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.acl-main.407</a>.
</div></div></section>
<section id="generalization-emerges-naturally-if-the-input-space-is-large" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="generalization-emerges-naturally-if-the-input-space-is-large">Generalization Emerges “Naturally” if the Input Space is Large</h3>
<ul>
<li>Presents an experiment showing that emergent languages are able to generalize to unseen combinations as long as input size is sufficiently large.</li>
<li>Discusses how the results challenge claims in the recent literature that deep networks fail to generalize.</li>
<li>Notes that the minimum channel capacity required for the emergence of a generalizing language is significantly larger than the minimum channel capacity required for a perfectly compositional language.</li>
<li>Presents additional experiments in the Appendix analyzing the effects of agent capacity and input density on generalization.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="generalization-does-not-require-compositionality" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="generalization-does-not-require-compositionality">Generalization Does Not Require Compositionality</h3>
<ul>
<li>Presents results showing that there is no correlation between compositionality and generalization ability.</li>
<li>Analyzes the language of a specific run with near-perfect generalization accuracy and medium posdis score.</li>
<li>Discusses how the analyzed language uses a “leaky disentanglement” strategy where two positions largely specialize as predictors of two attributes, respectively, but a third more entangled position is still necessary for perfect communication.</li>
<li>Briefly analyzes in the Appendix a language with near-perfect generalization accuracy and very low posdis score.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="compositionality-and-ease-of-transmission" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compositionality-and-ease-of-transmission">Compositionality and Ease of Transmission</h3>
<ul>
<li>Discusses the hypothesis that compositional languages are easier to decode and transmit to new learners.</li>
<li>Presents an experiment where new Receivers are trained on frozen Senders that achieved a high level of generalization accuracy.</li>
<li>Finds that learning speed and generalization accuracy of new Receivers are strongly positively correlated with degree of compositionality.</li>
<li>Mentions further experiments in the Appendix that replicate the ease-of-transmission analysis across various channel capacities.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h3>
<ul>
<li>Summarizes the main findings of the paper, highlighting the results that challenge common assumptions in the emergent language literature.</li>
<li>Relates the findings to the ongoing debate on the origins of compositionality in natural language.</li>
<li>Discusses the potential benefits of compositionality for developing languages that are quickly usable by wide communities of artificial agents.</li>
<li>Highlights the connection between compositionality and disentanglement in representation learning.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="my-thoughts" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-thoughts">My Thoughts</h2>
<p>We have three main results:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Generalization Emerges “Naturally” if the Input Space is Large</strong></li>
<li><strong>No Correlation Between Compositionality and Generalization</strong></li>
<li><strong>Compositionality increases Ease of Transmission</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>From a simple analysis of the lewis signaling game. The cost of coordination for an non compositional language is exponential in the number of states. For a compositional language the cost can reduced an exponential of the size of the lexicon (number of atomic signals) plus some constant factor for learning the grammar if it is some small set of aggregation rules. (Usually one rule is sufficient to support compositionality).</p>
<p>The lewis signaling game is more or less guaranteed to converge to some a signaling system<sup>1</sup> with the suitable algorithm. Without a good algorithm the game is more likely to converge to a partial pooling equilibrium where payoffs are less than 1 due to one side or both being unable to conflate different states.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;one that has an expected payoff of 1</p></div></div><p>What this means is that all things being equal the compositional language will emerge much sooner the the non compositional language given the opportunity to do so. So why don’t we see this.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>When the number of states isn’t larger than the number of basic signals it is easier to learn a non compositional language. So we should put a cap on the number of basic signals.</li>
<li>The multiplier for learning grammar may be big especially if we use a neural network, more so if the grammar is complicates. So if we don’t see compositionality perhaps we need to make the grammar simpler or the state space bigger.</li>
<li>This is theoretical - perhaps since we use a neural network rather then a tabular RL solution we need lots of data to learn anything. As we go though the epoch there may be enough rounds in the lewis game for use to establish a convention without the need for compositionality.</li>
<li>Ok Let’s say we have a fast learning algorithm and a big but manageable input space. Do we get compositionality. The answer is not necessarily.</li>
</ol>
<p>Let dive deeper into this last point:</p>
<p>Despite what Chat GPT will tell you if you ask the lewis signaling game only outputs simple languages. No complex signals, no grammar, no recursion and no compositionality. It has many possible equilibria and none correspond to a language complex signals or grammar.</p>
<p>For grammar and complex signals to emerge you need to tweak the lewis signaling game. <span class="citation" data-cites="skyrms2010signals">(Skyrms 2010)</span> reports on a couple of papers which produce complex signals. Most of the interesting work came out after the book. Regardless in the papers the agents were given a simple aggregation rule to follow. The conjunction leads to a bag of words. The concatenation leads to sequences. But what they don’t seem to stress is that for a complex signals we want a state that decomposes into a way we can match in our aggregation rule. Think group homomorphism. And there may be multiple decompositions so think normal subgroups.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-skyrms2010signals" class="csl-entry">
Skyrms, Brian. 2010. <span>“<span class="nocase">14512 Complex Signals and Compositionality</span>.”</span> In <em><span class="nocase">Signals: Evolution, Learning, and Information</span></em>. Oxford University Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199580828.003.0013">https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199580828.003.0013</a>.
</div></div><p>There isn’t a how to guide to get the agents to use some arbitrary grammar. (Not AFAIK). There are a bunch of books and many papers but they don’t seem to have a the kind of recipes that are needed here. In my view most of these books look for the answers based on what they know rather what they need to know. They may have fascinating points but lead to greater confusion rather then more clarity.</p>
<p>One abstraction I came across is that the notion of a grammar is essentially a decision tree mapping the signals back into the state. Decision trees sounds simple enough but this tree is not given but needs to be learned by trial and error. Signals due to successes are sparse. There might be a setting in which a sender can construct the tree and then the receiver just needs to learn it. But it requires the sender to have access to the distribution of states and sub states. This distribution can be used to come up with a tree that is optimal for a given set of signals. If the sender and receiver don’t have access to this distribution the can learn it. But my work indicates that to learn the distribution to a high degree of accuracy requires more turns then my lewis signaling algorithm does. At least for simple signaling systems.</p>
<p>For a simple signaling system I developed two algorithms. THe first learned a signaling system. The second first enumerated all signaling systems of a certain size and then selected one from those it believed were optimal. Each new state would reduce the belief until the sender and receiver had a common belief. This may not scale but can adapt to new distributions seamlessly. I thought about a similar approach for working with complex grammars. But In this case I did not have an efficient way to enumerate all possible grammars. However there seems to be a way to do this. Instead of considering all decision trees, we can instead consider just huffman trees. These means that the sender and receiver use the lewis signaling game to learn a shared huffman tree. The outcome is that the tree should compress the state space. The only problem is that such a grammar is not likely to be compositional and would be very difficult to learn for humans.</p>
<p>So what we need is for the agents to learn the tree interactively. Two approaches come to mind and these are 1. huffman coding - which builds the tree but doesn’t update it to account for distributional shits. 2. Vitter algorithm for adaptive huffman coding - which updates the tree as new states are seen. THis is 3. adaptive arithmetic coding - which is a generalization of adaptive huffman coding.</p>
<p>One point to consider is that such a grammar is likely to provide a good compression of the state space. This is due to the these algorithms also being compression algorithms.</p>
<p>I would imagine that the output of such a grammar to be a binary sequence. This suggest that this would lead to a entangled representation with no discernable compositional structure.</p>
<p>Now there are reputedly many languages with very simple grammars. But the ones we are familiar with are not simple. They also have large lexicons. We need to put that aside and look for ways to work with simple grammars. It is quite possible to come up with two or three rules that can generate both morphology and a recursive syntax. It might be possible with one rule.</p>
<p>Ok lets briefly consider the other two points.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Compositionality and Generalization in Emergent Languages"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>Compositionality and Generalization in Emergent Languages</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>there is also a video at</p>
<p><a href="https://slideslive.com/38928781/compositionality-and-generalization-in-emergent-languages">video</a></p>
</section>
<section id="the-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-code">The code</h2>
<p>and code at</p>
<p><a href="https://paperswithcode.com/paper/compositionality-and-generalization-in">papers with code</a></p>
<p>and even the colab link to</p>
<p><a href="https://colab.research.google.com/github/facebookresearch/EGG/blob/main/tutorials/EGG%20walkthrough%20with%20a%20MNIST%20autoencoder.ipynb">EGG walkthrough</a></p>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2025,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Compositionality and {Generalization} in {Emergent}
    {Languages}},
  date = {2025-01-01},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/compositionality-and-generalization/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2025. <span>“Compositionality and Generalization in
Emergent Languages.”</span> January 1, 2025. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/compositionality-and-generalization/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/compositionality-and-generalization/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>review</category>
  <category>compositionality</category>
  <category>neural networks</category>
  <category>signaling systems</category>
  <category>language evolution</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/compositionality-and-generalization/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/compositionality-and-generalization/thumbnail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Emergent Communication of Generalizations</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/emergent-communication-of-generelization/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>I think this is an amazing paper. I read it critically and made copious notes to see what I could learn from it. The paper point out some limitations of Lewis referential games^[In this game the sender sees images, it needs to classify them into some representation and sends a message. The reciever gets the same or similar images + distractors, it needs to run a classifier and needs to select the correct one. Learning an image classifier per agent is expensive and requires access to both an an image classification is likely shared. This however presents a problem…. It allows the agents? ] and suggest a couple of extentions that can over come these limitations. There is</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="mu2022emergentcomms">(Mu and Goodman 2021)</span></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-mu2022emergentcomms" class="csl-entry">
Mu, Jesse, and Noah D. Goodman. 2021. <span>“Emergent Communication of Generalizations.”</span> <em>CoRR</em> abs/2106.02668. <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.02668">https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.02668</a>.
</div></div></section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>To build agents that can collaborate effectively with others, recent research has trained artificial agents to communicate with each other in Lewis-style referential games. However, this often leads to successful but uninterpretable communication. We argue that this is due to the game objective: communicating about a single object in a shared visual context is prone to overfitting and does not encourage language useful beyond concrete reference. In contrast, human language conveys a rich variety of abstract ideas. To promote such skills, we propose games that require communicating generalizations over sets of objects representing abstract visual concepts, optionally with separate contexts for each agent. We find that these games greatly improve systematicity and interpretability of the learned languages, according to several metrics in the literature. Finally, we propose a method for identifying logical operations embedded in the emergent languages by learning an approximate compositional reconstruction of the language.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-video" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-video">The Video</h2>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LVW_t7p42X0" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The Paper</h2>
<p>Here is the paper with my annotation and highlights.</p>
</section>
<section id="annotations" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="annotations">Annotations</h2>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>To promote such skills, propose games that require communicating generalizations over sets of objects representing abstract visual concepts, optionally with separate contexts for each agent. <sup>1</sup></p>
<div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;Significant modification the game: tweak payoffs, assign categories to symbols and allow sending of categories.</p></div></blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We argue that the reference games typically used in these studies are ill-suited to drive linguistic <em>systematicity</em> for two reasons <sup>2</sup></p>
<div id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;The best the original Lewis signaling game can do is establish a one to one convention between a sender’s siganal of states and reciever action per states. This is just a coordination part of communication.</p></div></blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>These tasks are more difficult <sup>3</sup></p>
<div id="fn3"><p><sup>3</sup>&nbsp;adding categories can result in a combinatorial increase the total messages. So that the agents need to coordinate on one of many more equilibria. Also you now want the agents to learn a much narrower subset of those possible equilibrium i.e.&nbsp;those that are are faithfull to certain structures in of the states. This is essentially a new problem which could be embodies as a second step after the Lewis game. There is no guarantee in general that such a structure exists. And as the authors suggest other structures are not considered</p></div></blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In the <strong>set reference</strong> (setref) game, a teacher must communicate to a student not just a single object, but rather a group of objects belonging to a concept <sup>4</sup></p>
<div id="fn4"><p><sup>4</sup>&nbsp;this is an interesting game - and also similar to <span class="cn">add reference</span> one modifies the game to refer to set of states by adding and, or and not operators giving an agent an basic reasoning ability. The new signaling systems allows specifying many more states. This can be useful in many applications. Of course learning to send additional operators becomes trivial conceptually if not in the practical sense</p></div></blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>These tasks are more difficult than traditional reference games <sup>5</sup></p>
<div id="fn5"><p><sup>5</sup>&nbsp;a “concept” like a red triangle is a specific type of a set. so this should be a easier task than the set reference. The difficulty seems to be not in the language or the categories but in the added classification of varied visual representation of seagulls</p></div></blockquote>
</div></div><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf#page=1" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf#page=1" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf#page=2" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf#page=2" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2024,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Emergent {Communication} of {Generalizations}},
  date = {2024-10-09},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/emergent-communication-of-generelization/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2024. <span>“Emergent Communication of
Generalizations.”</span> October 9, 2024. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/emergent-communication-of-generelization/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/emergent-communication-of-generelization/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>signaling games</category>
  <category>stub</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/emergent-communication-of-generelization/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/emergent-communication-of-generelization/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Evolutionary dynamics of Lewis signaling games: signaling systems vs. partial pooling</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2009/HutteggerSkryms2009/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="huttegger2010evolutionary">(Huttegger et al. 2010)</span></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-huttegger2010evolutionary" class="csl-entry">
Huttegger, Simon M, Brian Skyrms, Rory Smead, and Kevin JS Zollman. 2010. <span>“Evolutionary Dynamics of Lewis Signaling Games: Signaling Systems Vs. Partial Pooling.”</span> <em>Synthese</em> 172: 177–91.
</div></div></section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Abstract Transfer of information between senders and receivers, of one kind or another, is essential to all life. David Lewis introduced a game theoretic model of the simplest case, where one sender and one receiver have pure common interest. How hard or easy is it for evolution to achieve information transfer in Lewis signaling?. The answers involve surprising subtleties. We discuss some if these in terms of evolutionary dynamics in both finite and infinite populations, with and without mutation.</p>
</section>
<section id="this-paper" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="this-paper">This paper</h2>
<p>I’ve not looked too deeply into this paper as it needs a deep dive into evolutionary dynamics which I’ve yet to study in depth. My intererst are RL and complex signaling systems. Some of the results in evolutionary dynamics can be directly applied to reinforcement learning.</p>
<p>The paper looks at moran processes and mutations. This is interesting in the open ended setting of language evolution.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Because this is a partnership game, average payoff is a <strong>Lyapunov function</strong> <sup>1</sup> for the system [in fact, it is even a potential function; see <span class="citation" data-cites="hofbauer1998evolutionary">(Hofbauer and Sigmund 1998)</span> ].</p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;<strong>Lyapunov functions</strong> are scalar functions that may be used to prove the stability of an equilibrium of an ODE</p></div><div id="ref-hofbauer1998evolutionary" class="csl-entry">
Hofbauer, Josef, and Karl Sigmund. 1998. <em>Evolutionary Games and Population Dynamics</em>. Cambridge university press.
</div></div></div>
<p>The look at Lyapunov functions and the replicator dynamics. This is interesting in the context stability of equilibria in signaling games.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>raises the same questions in the context of evolution in finite populations with fixed population size (via the Moran process with and without mutation)</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The Paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2024,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Evolutionary Dynamics of {Lewis} Signaling Games: Signaling
    Systems Vs. Partial Pooling},
  date = {2024-10-08},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2009/HutteggerSkryms2009/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2024. <span>“Evolutionary Dynamics of Lewis Signaling
Games: Signaling Systems Vs. Partial Pooling.”</span> October 8, 2024.
<a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2009/HutteggerSkryms2009/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2009/HutteggerSkryms2009/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>signaling games</category>
  <category>evolutionary dynamics</category>
  <category>stub</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2009/HutteggerSkryms2009/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2009/HutteggerSkryms2009/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad: Retrofitting Cross-Lingual Word Embeddings to Dictionaries</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>This paper, “Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad: Retrofitting Cross-Lingual Word Embeddings to Dictionaries,” challenges the traditional view that overfitting is inherently detrimental when developing cross-lingual word embeddings (CLWE)<sup>1</sup> and that the evaluation of CLWE using Bilingual Lexicon Induction (BLI) is flawed.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;see my note below regarding this point.</p></div></div><div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Cross Language Word Embeddings (CLWE) in a nutshell
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Since I have not looked into CLWE before I add this outline on how CLWE are being learned from in the video lined below.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>embeddings are learned for each language</li>
<li>a Bilingual dictionary provides a mapping from word pairs which is used to tweak the embeddings so they align across languages.</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Cross-lingual word embeddings (CLWE) are often evaluated on bilingual lexicon induction (BLI). Recent CLWE methods use linear projections, which underfit the training dictionary, to generalize on BLI. However, underfitting can hinder generalization to other downstream tasks that rely on words from the training dictionary. We address this limitation by retrofitting CLWE to the training dictionary, which pulls training translation pairs closer in the embedding space and overfits the training dictionary. This simple post-processing step often improves accuracy on two downstream tasks, despite lowering BLI test accuracy. We also retrofit to both the training dictionary and a synthetic dictionary induced from CLWE, which sometimes generalizes even better on downstream tasks. Our results confirm the importance of fully exploiting the training dictionary in downstream tasks and explains why BLI is a flawed CLWE evaluation.computational resources to train.</p>
<p>— <span class="citation" data-cites="Zhang2020XLingEmbedd">(Zhang et al. 2020)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Zhang2020XLingEmbedd" class="csl-entry">
Zhang, Mozhi, Yoshinari Fujinuma, Michael J. Paul, and Jordan Boyd-Graber. 2020. <span>“Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad: Retrofitting Cross-Lingual Word Embeddings to Dictionaries.”</span> In <em>Association for Computational Linguistics</em>. The Cyberverse Simulacrum of Seattle. <a href="http://umiacs.umd.edu/~jbg//docs/2020_acl_refine.pdf">http://umiacs.umd.edu/~jbg//docs/2020_acl_refine.pdf</a>.
</div></div></div>
</section>
<section id="key-points" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-points">Key Points:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Traditional Evaluation of CLWE</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Cross-lingual word embeddings (CLWE) typically aim to map words from different languages into a shared vector space.</li>
<li>They are commonly evaluated using Bilingual Lexicon Induction (BLI), which tests the model’s ability to translate words based on a set of test words.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Underfitting in Projection-Based CLWE</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Current CLWE methods, particularly linear projection-based ones, underfit the training dictionary. This means they don’t perfectly align all translation pairs in the training data.</li>
<li>The paper argues that this underfitting, while beneficial for BLI test accuracy, can hinder performance on downstream tasks where words from the training dictionary play a critical role.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Retrofitting Approach</strong>:
<ul>
<li>The authors propose retrofitting as a post-processing step to bring training translation pairs closer in the embedding space, essentially overfitting the training dictionary.</li>
<li>This retrofitting involves modifying the embeddings to minimize distances between training translation pairs while retaining as much of the original structure as possible.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Retrofitting to Synthetic Dictionaries:
<ul>
<li>In addition to the training dictionary, the paper introduces retrofitting to a synthetic dictionary induced from the original CLWE using the Cross-Domain Similarity Local Scaling (CSLS) heuristic.</li>
<li>This helps balance the need to fit the training dictionary while maintaining some generalization capability for unseen words.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="experimental-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="experimental-results">Experimental Results:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>BLI Accuracy</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Retrofitting the embeddings to the training dictionary results in perfect alignment of training pairs, leading to decreased BLI test accuracy since the embeddings overfit the training data.</li>
<li>However, retrofitting to a synthetic dictionary can achieve a balance, improving BLI test accuracy somewhat while still fitting the training data better.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Downstream Tasks</strong>:
<ul>
<li>The authors evaluates the retrofitted embeddings on two downstream tasks: <strong>document classification</strong> and <strong>dependency parsing</strong>.</li>
<li>Despite lower BLI test accuracy, retrofitted embeddings often lead to improved performance on these tasks. This underscores the importance of fully exploiting the training dictionary for downstream performance.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="main-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="main-contributions">Main Contributions:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Challenge to BLI as a Sole Metric</strong>:
<ul>
<li>The authors argues that BLI accuracy does not always correlate with downstream task performance, revealing the limitations of relying solely on BLI for evaluating CLWE.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Retrofitting as a Beneficial Overfitting</strong>:
<ul>
<li>It shows that overfitting to the training dictionary through retrofitting can be beneficial, enhancing the performance of downstream tasks even if it harms BLI test accuracy.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Synthetic Dictionary for Balance:
<ul>
<li>Introducing the use of a synthetic dictionary for retrofitting provides a middle ground, balancing the need to fit the training dictionary while retaining some generalization ability.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion:</h2>
<p>The authors suggest that the overemphasis on BLI as an evaluation metric for CLWE should be reconsidered, advocating instead for a focus on downstream tasks that better reflect the utility of the embeddings. They propose that future work might explore more complex non-linear projections to better fit the dictionary without compromising on generalization.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h2>
<p>The paper’s main takeaway is that overfitting to the training dictionary via retrofitting is not inherently harmful. In fact, it can lead to better performance on downstream NLP tasks. This insight invites a reconsideration of the evaluation metrics for cross-lingual word embeddings and opens the door for future work on more sophisticated retrofitting and projection methods.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
overfitting
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>It is not surprising that the authors ‘discovered’ that fitting the model on <code>test</code> + <code>train</code> + <code>validation</code> gives better results then fitting on <code>train</code> part only. After all the best way to reduce overfitting is to give it more data.</li>
<li>This is a common practice in machine learning to train on the full dataset once we have used to get the best results when the model is deployed to production.</li>
<li>Bayesian LOO Cross validation also allows one to measure the generalization error of the model without having to make the sacrifice of a train/test split.</li>
<li>Considering that the dataset is a dictionary means there is probably little noise to overfit on.</li>
</ul>
<p>On the other hand their criticism of BLI as a metric is valid. There are lots of bad metrics and it is more so when we wish to use it to estimate performance on a different task. In RL one uses importance sampling to make the correction between on policy and off policy - perhaps this is something to look into, though it would be easier to do this if this was a RL problem rather than supervised ML.</p>
<p>It is a common practice in machine learning to use a proxy metric to evaluate the model. The problem is that the proxy metric is not always a good indicator of the model’s performance on the real task. This is why it is important to evaluate the model on the real task as well.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="see-also" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="see-also">See also</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://users.umiacs.umd.edu/~jbg/docs/2020_acl_refine.pdf">Paper</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yVN47wGkCko">Video</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/zhangmozhi/retrofit_clwe">Code</a></li>
</ul>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2024,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Why {Overfitting} {Isn’t} {Always} {Bad:} {Retrofitting}
    {Cross-Lingual} {Word} {Embeddings} to {Dictionaries}},
  date = {2024-06-11},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2024. <span>“Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad:
Retrofitting Cross-Lingual Word Embeddings to Dictionaries.”</span> June
11, 2024. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/Why
Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2020/Why Overfitting Isn’t Always Bad/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Multi-agent Reinforcement Learning in Sequential Social Dilemmas</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2017/MARL-in-sequential-social-dilemmas/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Matrix games like Prisoner’s Dilemma have guided research on social dilemmas for decades. However, they necessarily treat the choice to cooperate or defect as an atomic action. In real-world social dilemmas these choices are temporally extended. Cooperativeness is a property that applies to policies, not elementary actions. We introduce sequential social dilemmas that share the mixed incentive structure of matrix game social dilemmas but also require agents to learn policies that implement their strategic intentions. We analyze the dynamics of policies learned by multiple self-interested independent learning agents, each using its own deep Qnetwork, on two Markov games we introduce here: 1. a fruit Gathering game and 2. a Wolfpack hunting game. We characterize how learned behavior in each domain changes as a function of environmental factors including resource abundance. Our experiments show how conflict can emerge from competition over shared resources and shed light on how the sequential nature of real world social dilemmas affects cooperation.” – <span class="citation" data-cites="leibo2017multi">(Leibo et al. 2017)</span> abstract</p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Initially at least it seems to me that the “sequential social dilemma” is just an analog of an iterated prisoner’s dilemma game. This game considered the basis of all other social dilemmas has been treated at great length in <span class="citation" data-cites="axelrod2009evolution">(Axelrod 2009)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="axelrod1997complexity">(Axelrod 1997)</span> with the famous Axelrod tournaments. Some interesting results include the fact that the best strategy in the tournament was the simplest. Population dynamics are such that in population of agents with one strategy, the introduction of new agents with a different strategy can gain a foothold and cause the dominant strategy in the population to switch to the new strategy. This is known as the “evolution of cooperation”.</p>
<p>This work led to a growing interest in the study of cooperation in non-cooperative games with about 300 new papers published on the topic in the 10 years following the publication.</p>
<p>Later work looked at the robustness of the winning strategies in the Axelrod tournaments, see <span class="citation" data-cites="nowak2004emergence">(Nowak et al. 2004)</span>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-nowak2004emergence" class="csl-entry">
Nowak, Martin A, Akira Sasaki, Christine Taylor, and Drew Fudenberg. 2004. <span>“Emergence of Cooperation and Evolutionary Stability in Finite Populations.”</span> <em>Nature</em> 428 (6983): 646–50.
</div></div><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-axelrod1997complexity" class="csl-entry">
Axelrod, R. 1997. <em>The Complexity of Cooperation: Agent-Based Models of Competition and Collaboration</em>. Princeton Studies in Complexity. Princeton University Press. <a href="https://books.google.co.il/books?id=J0dgRGMdjmQC">https://books.google.co.il/books?id=J0dgRGMdjmQC</a>.
</div></div><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-axelrod2009evolution" class="csl-entry">
———. 2009. <em>The Evolution of Cooperation: Revised Edition</em>. Basic Books. <a href="https://books.google.co.il/books?id=SwU4DgAAQBAJ">https://books.google.co.il/books?id=SwU4DgAAQBAJ</a>.
</div></div><section id="outline" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="outline">Outline</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Introduction
<ul>
<li><p>Discusses the tension in social dilemmas between individual rationality and collective rationality.</p></li>
<li><p>Presents three canonical examples of matrix game social dilemmas: Prisoner’s Dilemma, Chicken, and Stag Hunt.</p></li>
<li><p>Discusses limitations of the matrix game social dilemma (MGSD) formalism.</p></li>
<li><p>Proposes a Sequential Social Dilemma (SSD) model.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Definitions and Notation
<ul>
<li><p>Defines SSDs as general-sum Markov games where policies, rather than actions, are classified as cooperation or defection.</p></li>
<li><p>Presents formal definitions of Markov games and SSDs, including the concept of empirical payoff matrices.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<!-- -->
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Learning Algorithms
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Discusses previous work on multi-agent learning in Markov games, taking a descriptive rather than a prescriptive view.</li>
<li>Describes the use of deep Q-networks (DQN) for learning in SSDs, assuming independent learners that treat each other as part of the environment.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Simulation Methods
<ul>
<li><p>Describes the implementation of Gathering and Wolfpack games in a 2D grid-world environment.</p></li>
<li><p>Specifies state representation, observation function, action space, reward structure, episode length, and DQN architecture.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<!-- -->
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li><p>Results</p>
<ul>
<li>Presents three experiments exploring the effects of environmental and agent parameters on emergent social outcomes.</li>
</ul>
<ol type="1">
<li>Experiment 1: Gathering
<ul>
<li><p>Describes the Gathering game, where players collect apples and can tag each other with a beam.</p></li>
<li><p>Discusses the influence of apple abundance (Napple) and conflict cost (Ntagged) on the emergence of aggressive (beam-use) behavior.</p></li>
<li><p>Shows that empirical game-theoretic analysis reveals Prisoner’s Dilemma-type payoffs in most cases where social dilemma conditions are met.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Experiment 2: Wolfpack
<ul>
<li><p>Describes the Wolfpack game, where two wolves cooperate to hunt prey and receive higher rewards for joint captures.</p></li>
<li><p>Investigates the impact of group capture bonus (rteam/rlone) and capture radius on the level of cooperation (wolves per capture).</p></li>
<li><p>Demonstrates that empirical payoff matrices in Wolfpack can exhibit Chicken, Stag Hunt, and Prisoner’s Dilemma characteristics.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Experiment 3: Agent Parameters Influencing the Emergence of Defection
<ul>
<li><p>Explores the effects of agent parameters (discount factor, batch size, and network size) on the emergence of defection in Gathering and Wolfpack.</p></li>
<li><p>Shows that agents with higher discount factors are more likely to defect, while larger batch sizes promote cooperation.</p></li>
<li><p>Highlights the opposite effects of network size on defection: increasing in Gathering and decreasing in Wolfpack, explained by the complexity of learning different policies.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Discussion</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Discusses the differences in learning complexity for cooperative and defecting policies in Gathering and Wolfpack.</p></li>
<li><p>Argues that SSD models provide a richer framework for understanding social dilemmas compared to MGSDs.</p></li>
<li><p>Proposes several important learning-related phenomena that are not captured by MGSD models.</p></li>
<li><p>Suggests broader applications of SSDs to study real-world social dilemmas, including policy interventions and resource sustainability.</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="introduction" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Introduction</h1>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="leibo2017multi">(Leibo et al. 2017)</span>, the authors introduce a new class of social dilemmas, called sequential social dilemmas, which are inspired by the classic matrix game social dilemmas like the Prisoner’s Dilemma.</p>


<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-leibo2017multi" class="csl-entry">
Leibo, Joel Z, Vinicius Zambaldi, Marc Lanctot, Janusz Marecki, and Thore Graepel. 2017. <span>“Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning in Sequential Social Dilemmas.”</span> <em>arXiv Preprint arXiv:1702.03037</em>.
</div></div>
</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2024,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Multi-Agent {Reinforcement} {Learning} in {Sequential}
    {Social} {Dilemmas}},
  date = {2024-06-10},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2017/MARL-in-sequential-social-dilemmas/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2024. <span>“Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning in
Sequential Social Dilemmas.”</span> June 10, 2024. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2017/MARL-in-sequential-social-dilemmas/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2017/MARL-in-sequential-social-dilemmas/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>paper review</category>
  <category>multi-agent reinforcement learning</category>
  <category>sequential social dilemmas</category>
  <category>sequential social dilemmas</category>
  <category>cooperation</category>
  <category>Markov games</category>
  <category>agent-based social simulation</category>
  <category>non-cooperative games</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2017/MARL-in-sequential-social-dilemmas/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Generally Capable Agents Emerge from Open-Ended Play</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/generally-capable-agents-emerge-from-open-ended-play/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="first-impressions" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="first-impressions">First impressions</h2>
<p>The paper does not present a breakthrough like alpha go zero etc. But it shows very high level of creativity and innovation. I am still a new comer to RL and this paper has opened my eyes to how little of the field I have seen. There are lots of buzz words, references to other papers and concepts that I am not familiar with. Also this paper is visually stunning. The authors have put a lot of energy into creating an aesthetically pleasing project and they have gone to some length to explain what would otherwise might be a very challenging evaluation process.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1yVoNAMLIy0" title="Max Jaderberg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<ol type="1">
<li>to what extent can agents learn to solve certain types of problems like solving a maze. I might call these learning tactical solutions</li>
<li>to what extent can agents compress this tactical knowledge into a heuristic that might end up as much more general.</li>
<li>to what extent can RL agents learn representations of the environment that allow them to reuse tactics and heuristics across different problems instead of having to discover them anew each time.</li>
<li>when sparse rewards or no rewards are given can agents learn use their capabilities to model the environment</li>
<li>generally capable agents should be able to handle the many different RL problem settings that are out there:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>single state, multi-state, continuous state,</li>
<li>tabular, continuous,</li>
<li>finite state space, infinite state space,</li>
<li>episodic, continuing, i.e.&nbsp;finite horizon, infinite horizon,</li>
<li>single agent, multi-agent,</li>
<li>online, offline,</li>
<li>model based, model free,</li>
<li>known dynamics, unknown dynamics,</li>
<li>sparse rewards, dense rewards,</li>
<li>on-policy, off-policy,</li>
<li>discounted, undiscounted rewards,</li>
<li>single goal, multi-goal,</li>
<li>deterministic, stochastic,</li>
<li>stationary, non-stationary,</li>
<li>specific constraints, in reality there are also variations of these settings not all of these are dichotomies.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>The paper mentions priors work on social dilemmas - another dimension that seems to be related is how well can agents learn to solve simple game theoretic scenarios like the prisoner’s dilemma or colonel Blotto and then to transfer the knowledge to more complex games. The same idea might be applied to problems based in economic models.</li>
</ol>
<p>here are some of the concepts that I am not familiar with:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/population-based-training-of-neural-networks/">Population based training</a> a technique used to optimize a series of NN at the same time.
<ul>
<li>can this be useful in RL where an agent might need to learn multiple NNs to solve a problem.
<ul>
<li>the transition model P(s’ | s, a) model</li>
<li>the reward model R(r | s, a) model</li>
<li>for representing the model (this is the four part dynamic function for <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f(s',r%7Cs,a)"></li>
<li>value functions
<ul>
<li>the value function, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?v_%7B%5Cpi_%7B%5Cstar%7D%20%7D%20(s)"></li>
<li>the action value function <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?q_%7B%5Cpi_%7B%5Cstar%7D%20%7D(s,a)"></li>
</ul></li>
<li>the advantage function <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?A_%7B%5Cpi_%7B%5Cstar%7D%20%7D(s,a)=%20Q_%7B%5Cpi_%7B%5Cstar%7D%20%7D(s,a)%20-%20V_%7B%5Cpi_%7B%5Cstar%7D%20%7D(s)"></li>
<li>the the policy <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?pi_%5Cstar%20(s)"></li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 29%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 9%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 13%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Algorithm</th>
<th>Abr</th>
<th>Q-Fn<br>
<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Q(s,a)"></th>
<th>V-Fn<br>
<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?V(s)"></th>
<th>Policy<br>
<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CF%80(a%E2%88%A3s)"></th>
<th>Advantage<br>
<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?A(s,a)"></th>
<th>Transitions<br>
<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P(s%E2%80%B2%E2%88%A3s,a)"></th>
<th>Reward <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?R(s,a)"></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Deep Q-Network<br>
<span class="citation" data-cites="Mnih2015HumanlevelCT">(Mnih et al. 2015)</span></td>
<td>(DQN)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><p>Double DQN</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Hasselt2015DeepRL">(Hasselt, Guez, and Silver 2015)</span></p></td>
<td>(DDQN)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Dueling DQN<br>
<span class="citation" data-cites="Wang2015DuelingNA">(Wang et al. 2015)</span></td>
<td></td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Deep Deterministic Policy Gradients<br>
<span class="citation" data-cites="Lillicrap2015ContinuousCW">(Lillicrap et al. 2015)</span></td>
<td>(DDPG)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><p>Twin Delayed DDPG</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Fujimoto2018AddressingFA">(Fujimoto, Hoof, and Meger 2018)</span></p></td>
<td>(TD3)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><p>Soft Actor-Critic</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Haarnoja2018SoftAO">(Haarnoja et al. 2018)</span></p></td>
<td>(SAC)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><p>Proximal Policy Optimization</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Schulman2017ProximalPO">(Schulman et al. 2017)</span></p></td>
<td>(PPO)</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><p>Trust Region Policy Optimization</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Schulman2015TrustRP">(Schulman et al. 2015)</span></p></td>
<td>(TRPO)</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Advantage Actor-Critic<br>
<span class="citation" data-cites="Mnih2016AsynchronousMF">(Mnih et al. 2016)</span></td>
<td>(A2C/A3C)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Model-Based DQN<br>
<span class="citation" data-cites="Feinberg2018ModelBasedVE">(Feinberg et al. 2018)</span></td>
<td>(M-DQN)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Model-Based PPO<br>
<span class="citation" data-cites="Clavera2018ModelBasedRL">(Clavera et al. 2018)</span></td>
<td>(M-PPO)</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><p>AlphaGo</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Silver2016MasteringTG">(Silver et al. 2016)</span></p></td>
<td></td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><p>AlphaGo Zero</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Silver2017MasteringTG">(Silver et al. 2017)</span></p></td>
<td></td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><p>AlphaZero</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Silver2018AGR">(Silver et al. 2018)</span></p></td>
<td></td>
<td>No</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Mnih2015HumanlevelCT" class="csl-entry">
Mnih, Volodymyr, K. Kavukcuoglu, David Silver, Andrei A. Rusu, J. Veness, Marc G. Bellemare, Alex Graves, et al. 2015. <span>“Human-Level Control Through Deep Reinforcement Learning.”</span> <em>Nature</em> 518: 529–33.
</div><div id="ref-Hasselt2015DeepRL" class="csl-entry">
Hasselt, H. V., A. Guez, and David Silver. 2015. <span>“Deep Reinforcement Learning with Double q-Learning,”</span> 2094–2100.
</div><div id="ref-Wang2015DuelingNA" class="csl-entry">
Wang, Ziyun, T. Schaul, Matteo Hessel, H. V. Hasselt, Marc Lanctot, and Nando de Freitas. 2015. <span>“Dueling Network Architectures for Deep Reinforcement Learning,”</span> 1995–2003.
</div><div id="ref-Lillicrap2015ContinuousCW" class="csl-entry">
Lillicrap, T., Jonathan J. Hunt, A. Pritzel, N. Heess, Tom Erez, Yuval Tassa, David Silver, and Daan Wierstra. 2015. <span>“Continuous Control with Deep Reinforcement Learning.”</span> <em>CoRR</em> abs/1509.02971.
</div><div id="ref-Fujimoto2018AddressingFA" class="csl-entry">
Fujimoto, Scott, H. V. Hoof, and D. Meger. 2018. <span>“Addressing Function Approximation Error in Actor-Critic Methods,”</span> 1582–91.
</div><div id="ref-Haarnoja2018SoftAO" class="csl-entry">
Haarnoja, Tuomas, Aurick Zhou, P. Abbeel, and S. Levine. 2018. <span>“Soft Actor-Critic: Off-Policy Maximum Entropy Deep Reinforcement Learning with a Stochastic Actor.”</span> <em>ArXiv</em> abs/1801.01290.
</div><div id="ref-Schulman2017ProximalPO" class="csl-entry">
Schulman, John, Filip Wolski, Prafulla Dhariwal, Alec Radford, and Oleg Klimov. 2017. <span>“Proximal Policy Optimization Algorithms.”</span> <em>ArXiv</em> abs/1707.06347.
</div><div id="ref-Schulman2015TrustRP" class="csl-entry">
Schulman, John, S. Levine, P. Abbeel, Michael I. Jordan, and Philipp Moritz. 2015. <span>“Trust Region Policy Optimization.”</span> <em>ArXiv</em> abs/1502.05477.
</div><div id="ref-Mnih2016AsynchronousMF" class="csl-entry">
Mnih, Volodymyr, Adrià Puigdomènech Badia, Mehdi Mirza, Alex Graves, T. Lillicrap, Tim Harley, David Silver, and K. Kavukcuoglu. 2016. <span>“Asynchronous Methods for Deep Reinforcement Learning,”</span> 1928–37.
</div><div id="ref-Feinberg2018ModelBasedVE" class="csl-entry">
Feinberg, Vladimir, Alvin Wan, I. Stoica, Michael I. Jordan, Joseph E. Gonzalez, and S. Levine. 2018. <span>“Model-Based Value Estimation for Efficient Model-Free Reinforcement Learning.”</span> <em>ArXiv</em> abs/1803.00101.
</div><div id="ref-Clavera2018ModelBasedRL" class="csl-entry">
Clavera, I., Jonas Rothfuss, John Schulman, Yasuhiro Fujita, T. Asfour, and P. Abbeel. 2018. <span>“Model-Based Reinforcement Learning via Meta-Policy Optimization,”</span> 617–29.
</div><div id="ref-Silver2016MasteringTG" class="csl-entry">
Silver, David, Aja Huang, Chris J. Maddison, A. Guez, L. Sifre, George van den Driessche, Julian Schrittwieser, et al. 2016. <span>“Mastering the Game of Go with Deep Neural Networks and Tree Search.”</span> <em>Nature</em> 529: 484–89.
</div><div id="ref-Silver2017MasteringTG" class="csl-entry">
Silver, David, Julian Schrittwieser, K. Simonyan, Ioannis Antonoglou, Aja Huang, A. Guez, T. Hubert, et al. 2017. <span>“Mastering the Game of Go Without Human Knowledge.”</span> <em>Nature</em> 550: 354–59.
</div><div id="ref-Silver2018AGR" class="csl-entry">
Silver, David, T. Hubert, Julian Schrittwieser, Ioannis Antonoglou, Matthew Lai, A. Guez, Marc Lanctot, et al. 2018. <span>“A General Reinforcement Learning Algorithm That Masters Chess, Shogi, and Go Through Self-Play.”</span> <em>Science</em> 362: 1140–44.
</div></div></section>
<section id="summary" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>The paper <span class="citation" data-cites="Team2021OpenEndedLL">(Team et al. 2021)</span> explores the idea that generally capable agents can emerge from open-ended play, similar to how human children learn and develop through play. The goal is to create agents that exhibit broad competencies and adaptability without being explicitly trained for specific tasks. In other words in the typical RL settings agents are trained to perform specific tasks and can learn solution to general problems. However they are very poor at generalizing these solutions to slightly different versions of the same problem. The authors seek to develop agents that can not only learn to solve a wide range of tasks but can also generalize and transfer their solutions to new problems.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Team2021OpenEndedLL" class="csl-entry">
Team, Open-Ended Learning, Adam Stooke, Anuj Mahajan, C. Barros, Charlie Deck, Jakob Bauer, Jakub Sygnowski, et al. 2021. <span>“Open-Ended Learning Leads to Generally Capable Agents.”</span> <em>ArXiv</em> abs/2107.12808.
</div><div id="ref-impala2018" class="csl-entry">
Espeholt, Lasse, Hubert Soyer, Remi Munos, Karen Simonyan, Volodymir Mnih, Tom Ward, Yotam Doron, et al. 2018. <span>“IMPALA: Scalable Distributed Deep-RL with Importance Weighted Actor-Learner Architectures.”</span> In <em>Proceedings of the International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)</em>.
</div><div id="ref-Hessel2018MultitaskDR" class="csl-entry">
Hessel, Matteo, Hubert Soyer, L. Espeholt, Wojciech M. Czarnecki, Simon Schmitt, and H. V. Hasselt. 2018. <span>“Multi-Task Deep Reinforcement Learning with PopArt.”</span> <em>ArXiv</em> abs/1809.04474.
</div></div><p>This is not the first time that this idea has been explored. Prior work includes the development of agents that can learn to play a variety of video games without explicit training on each game. Other work like <span class="citation" data-cites="impala2018">(Espeholt et al. 2018)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="Hessel2018MultitaskDR">(Hessel et al. 2018)</span> at deep mind have already shown how this can be done. However, the authors of this paper take this idea further by developing agents that can learn to solve a wider range of tasks.</p>
<p>In this paper they develop environments that co-evolve with the agents. The environment increase in difficulty as the agents learn to solve them. The agents are equipped with intrinsic motivation mechanisms, such as curiosity and novelty-seeking behaviors, to drive exploration. A variety of tasks and challenges are presented dynamically, promoting continuous learning and adaptation.</p>
<p>But the real question is to what degree does this approach create agents that can learn to solve a wide range of tasks and can generalize their solutions to new problems. There seems to be three parts</p>
</section>
<section id="open-ended-learning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="open-ended-learning">Open-Ended Learning:</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Open-Ended Learning</dt>
<dd>
<p>Open-ended learning refers to an unsupervised, exploratory process where agents interact with their environment without predefined goals. This approach contrasts with traditional reinforcement learning, which focuses on optimizing performance for specific tasks.</p>
</dd>
</dl>
<p>Have the the authors really provided environment with not predefined goals or just many many goals. There are games in game theory where the player</p>
<p>is given incomplete information - you don’t get told the reward or the rules and need to figure out an optimal strategy without them.</p>
</section>
<section id="methodology" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methodology">Methodology:</h2>
<p>The authors design an environment that encourages diverse interactions and challenges. Agents are equipped with intrinsic motivation mechanisms, such as curiosity and novelty-seeking behaviors, to drive exploration. A variety of tasks and challenges are presented dynamically, promoting continuous learning and adaptation.</p>
<p>As the authors point out - making a maze larger don’t necessarily make it more difficult once the agents have learned to solved a few mazes. The authors have to carefully design the environment to ensure that the agents are always challenged but not overwhelmed.</p>
<p>I have three criticism of the methodology:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although this paper is about RL there is more than a fair share of evolutionary algorithms. It isn’t clear to what extent the agents are learning through RL and to what extent they are evolving through evolutionary algorithms. I don’t dislike this idea but it seems to muddy the waters regarding how well this research might be applied to create generally capable RL agents in the real world.</li>
<li>Some of the environment used in testing are hand crafted while the bulk of the environments are procedurally generated.</li>
<li>The claim about these these hand crafted test environments being unlike other environments that are procedurally generated is not very convincing.</li>
</ol>
<p>How is skill acquisition tracked?</p>
<p>Intrinsic Motivations are based on curiosity and novelty seeking behaviors. However I think that for some environment/problems intrinsic (motivation) could emerge from a dynamic of the environment itself. In some way this intrinsic motivation reflects the agents ability to model the environment and to predict the consequences of its actions.</p>
<p>For example in an agent can reproduce under some selection pressure it should acquire a relevant fitness intrinsic (expected progeny). If it needs to solve different mazes it should need an exploration intrinsic. If it needs to maximize harvesting of resources it should learn some utility function intrinsic. For a social dilemma it might learn some social utility function intrinsic. However in this case this is an intrinsic that need to be learned by all agents Even if all the agents learn it there is are possibility that the agents will not cooperate. We might look to game theory, mechanism design to see if agents can learn self encouraging mechanisms to cooperate and so on. Can they learn to signal or coordinate behavior to activate the social utility function intrinsic. Can they plan to change roles in sequential games with memory and without.</p>
<p>a environment itself. For example in the case of the maze the agent might be intrinsically motivated to explore the maze because it is the only way to find the reward. In this case the environment itself is providing the intrinsic motivation.</p>
<p>A more interesting approach would be to track the agents ability to solve a wide range of tasks and to generalize their solutions to new problems. This would be a more direct measure of the agents general capabilities.</p>
<p>The paper and website show how the internal state of the agent is visualized over the course of play. This seems to be a hearmap with different possible goals.</p>
</section>
<section id="results-and-findings" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results-and-findings">Results and Findings:</h2>
<p>Agents developed through open-ended play demonstrate a wide range of capabilities, such as problem-solving, tool use, and social interaction. These agents outperform those trained with traditional task-specific reinforcement learning in terms of adaptability and generalization. Emergent behaviors and skills are observed, highlighting the potential of open-ended play in fostering general intelligence.</p>
</section>
<section id="implications-for-ai-development" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-for-ai-development">Implications for AI Development:</h2>
<p>The findings suggest that fostering environments that encourage open-ended play can lead to the development of more robust and versatile AI agents. This approach could be pivotal in advancing AI towards general intelligence, where agents can perform well across a wide range of tasks without explicit training for each.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions">Future Directions:</h2>
<p>Further research is needed to understand the mechanisms underlying the success of open-ended play. Scaling up the complexity of environments and intrinsic motivation systems could lead to even more capable agents. Exploring the integration of open-ended play with other AI paradigms might enhance the development of general AI.</p>
<!-- ![paper](https://arxiv.org/pdf/2107.12808){.col-page width="800px" height="1000px"} -->



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2024,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Generally {Capable} {Agents} {Emerge} from {Open-Ended}
    {Play}},
  date = {2024-06-10},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/generally-capable-agents-emerge-from-open-ended-play/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2024. <span>“Generally Capable Agents Emerge from
Open-Ended Play.”</span> June 10, 2024. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/generally-capable-agents-emerge-from-open-ended-play/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/generally-capable-agents-emerge-from-open-ended-play/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>paper review</category>
  <category>multi-agent reinforcement learning</category>
  <category>sequential social dilemmas</category>
  <category>sequential social dilemmas</category>
  <category>cooperation</category>
  <category>Markov games</category>
  <category>agent-based social simulation</category>
  <category>non-cooperative games</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2021/generally-capable-agents-emerge-from-open-ended-play/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>sense2vec - A Fast and Accurate Method for Word Sense Disambiguation In Neural Word Embeddings</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/sense2vec/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Sense2Vec</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="trask2015sense2vecfastaccurate">(Trask, Michalak, and Liu 2015)</span> is an interesting deep learning model based on word2vec that can learn more interesting and detailed word vectors from large corpora. Sense2Vec embeddings are for word senses rather than for tokens.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><p>The shortcoming of word2vec is that it only learns one vector per word, which is not enough to capture the multiple meanings of a word. Sense2Vec addresses this issue by learning multiple embeddings for each word based on supervised disambiguation. This allows a consuming NLP model to select a sense-disambiguated embedding quickly and accurately.</p>
<p>I thought that the next step would be to cluster these embeddings by contexts and thus arrive at a wordsense version - however it turns out this was computationally expensive and difficult to apply in a scalable fashion. The idea of this paper is to use a supervised approach to disambiguate the senses of words. This means that the words need to be tagged using thier part-of-speech (POS) tags or named entity resolution. This approach is faster and more accurate than the clustering approach. However there is a limitation that the supervised labels are required and there can be multiple wordsenses within a signle POS tag.</p>
<p>Abstract</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Neural word representations have proven useful in Natural Language Processing (NLP) tasks due to their ability to efficiently model complex semantic and syntactic word relationships. However, most techniques model only one representation per word, despite the fact that a single word can have multiple meanings or “senses”. Some techniques model words by using multiple vectors that are clustered based on context. However, recent neural approaches rarely focus on the application to a consuming NLP algorithm. Furthermore, the training process of recent word-sense models is expensive relative to single-sense embedding processes. This paper presents a novel approach which addresses these concerns by modeling multiple embeddings for each word based on supervised disambiguation, which provides a fast and accurate way for a consuming NLP model to select a sense-disambiguated embedding. We demonstrate that these embeddings can disambiguate both contrastive senses such as nominal and verbal senses as well as nuanced senses such as sarcasm. We further evaluate Part-of-Speech disambiguated embeddings on neural dependency parsing, yielding a greater than 8% average error reduction in unlabeled attachment scores across 6 languages.</p>
<p>— <span class="citation" data-cites="trask2015sense2vecfastaccurate">(Trask, Michalak, and Liu 2015)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></div>
<section id="review" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h2>
<p>The paper <span class="citation" data-cites="trask2015sense2vecfastaccurate">(Trask, Michalak, and Liu 2015)</span> the autors introduced a novel method for word sense disambiguation in neural word embeddings. Traditional word embedding techniques such as Word2Vec represent each word by a single vector, regardless of its multiple meanings or senses, which often leads to ambiguities. This challenge is known as the “superposition” problem, where multiple meanings of a word are combined into a single vector, potentially leading to suboptimal performance in downstream NLP tasks. SENSE2VEC addresses this limitation by generating multiple embeddings for each word, effectively disambiguating different senses.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-trask2015sense2vecfastaccurate" class="csl-entry">
Trask, Andrew, Phil Michalak, and John Liu. 2015. <span>“Sense2vec - a Fast and Accurate Method for Word Sense Disambiguation in Neural Word Embeddings.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1511.06388">https://arxiv.org/abs/1511.06388</a>.
</div></div></section>
<section id="motivation-and-related-work" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="motivation-and-related-work">Motivation and Related Work</h2>
<p>The motivation behind SENSE2VEC stems from the shortcomings of earlier models like Word2Vec and Wang2Vec. Word2Vec, while highly successful, does not consider the order of words in a sentence and struggles with polysemy—the phenomenon where a single word can have multiple meanings. Wang2Vec improves upon Word2Vec by incorporating word order, making it more suitable for syntactic tasks, yet still relies on single embeddings per word, making it less effective for handling polysemic words.</p>
<p>Other approaches, such as multi-prototype vector-space models by Reisinger and Mooney (2010), attempt to tackle polysemy by clustering the contexts in which a word appears and generating different embeddings for each cluster. However, these methods often require unsupervised clustering, making the process computationally expensive and difficult to apply in a scalable fashion. SENSE2VEC circumvents these challenges by leveraging supervised learning with part-of-speech (POS) tagging or named entity resolution, reducing the computational overhead while providing more accurate disambiguation.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-sense2vec-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-sense2vec-model">The SENSE2VEC Model</h2>
<p>The core innovation of SENSE2VEC lies in its use of supervised labels, such as POS tags, to disambiguate the senses of words. Unlike previous models that rely on unsupervised clustering methods, SENSE2VEC uses these labels to generate separate embeddings for each sense of a word. For example, the word “bank” can have distinct embeddings for its noun and verb forms.</p>
<p>The model can be trained using traditional methods like Continuous Bag of Words (CBOW) or Skip-gram, with a key difference: instead of predicting words given surrounding words, SENSE2VEC predicts word senses given surrounding senses. This approach leads to more accurate representations of polysemic words in context, reducing the negative impact of superposition.</p>
</section>
<section id="evaluation-and-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="evaluation-and-results">Evaluation and Results</h2>
<p>The authors evaluated SENSE2VEC on various NLP tasks, including dependency parsing and named entity resolution (NER). Notably, the disambiguation achieved by SENSE2VEC led to significant improvements in performance. For example, in dependency parsing across six languages (Bulgarian, German, English, French, Italian, and Swedish), SENSE2VEC embeddings resulted in an average error reduction of over 8% compared to the Wang2Vec baseline.</p>
<p>The model also demonstrated its effectiveness in handling sentiment disambiguation, as shown in Table 5 of the paper, where the word “bad” was successfully disambiguated into a negative and positive sentiment sense. The positive sense captured sarcastic uses of “bad,” which is often interpreted as “good” in informal language, while the negative sense retained the more classical meaning of “bad.”</p>
</section>
<section id="strengths-and-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strengths-and-contributions">Strengths and Contributions</h2>
<p>SENSE2VEC’s strengths lie in its efficiency and accuracy. By utilizing supervised labels, the model eliminates the need for expensive clustering algorithms, making it both faster and easier to scale. The ability to disambiguate nuanced senses of words, such as sentiment and named entities, showcases the flexibility and robustness of the approach.</p>
<p>Additionally, the model’s performance improvements in downstream tasks like dependency parsing and NER demonstrate its practical applicability in real-world NLP systems. The fact that SENSE2VEC outperforms earlier models like Wang2Vec and other clustering-based approaches highlights its contribution to the field of word sense disambiguation.</p>
</section>
<section id="limitations-and-future-work" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="limitations-and-future-work">Limitations and Future Work</h2>
<p>One potential limitation of SENSE2VEC is its reliance on labeled data. While supervised learning offers many advantages in terms of accuracy, it also introduces a dependency on the availability of high-quality labels. For languages or domains where such labels are scarce, applying SENSE2VEC may be more challenging.</p>
<p>The authors acknowledge this limitation and suggest that future work could explore the use of other types of supervised labels or investigate ways to combine both supervised and unsupervised methods to further enhance word sense disambiguation.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Overall, SENSE2VEC presents a compelling and efficient solution to the problem of word sense disambiguation in neural word embeddings. By leveraging supervised NLP labels, the model significantly improves the accuracy of embeddings for polysemic words, leading to better performance in NLP tasks like dependency parsing and NER. Its contribution to the field is clear, and it paves the way for future advancements in sense-disambiguated word embeddings.</p>
</section>
<section id="see-also" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="see-also">See also:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1511.06388">paper</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/explosion/sense2vec">code</a> by Explosion AI</li>
<li><a href="https://demos.explosion.ai/sense2vec">demo</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">from</span> sense2vec <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> Sense2Vec</span>
<span id="cb1-2"></span>
<span id="cb1-3">s2v <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Sense2Vec().from_disk(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/path/to/s2v_reddit_2015_md"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-4">query <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"natural_language_processing|NOUN"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">assert</span> query <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> s2v</span>
<span id="cb1-6">vector <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> s2v[query]</span>
<span id="cb1-7">freq <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> s2v.get_freq(query)</span>
<span id="cb1-8">most_similar <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> s2v.most_similar(query, n<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-9"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># [('machine_learning|NOUN', 0.8986967),</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#  ('computer_vision|NOUN', 0.8636297),</span></span>
<span id="cb1-11"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#  ('deep_learning|NOUN', 0.8573361)]</span></span></code></pre></div>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">from</span> sense2vec <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> Sense2Vec</span>
<span id="cb2-2">s2v <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Sense2Vec().from_disk(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"./s2v_reddit_2015_md"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-3">vector <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> s2v[<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"natural_language_processing|NOUN"</span>]</span>
<span id="cb2-4">most_similar <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> s2v.most_similar(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"duck|VERB"</span>, n<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">10</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-5"><span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">print</span>(most_similar)</span></code></pre></div>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2022,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Sense2vec - {A} {Fast} and {Accurate} {Method} for {Word}
    {Sense} {Disambiguation} {In} {Neural} {Word} {Embeddings}},
  date = {2022-06-26},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/sense2vec/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2022. <span>“Sense2vec - A Fast and Accurate Method for
Word Sense Disambiguation In Neural Word Embeddings.”</span> June 26,
2022. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/sense2vec/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/sense2vec/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/sense2vec/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Variational Inference with Normalizing Flows</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./fig_1.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="figure 1"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/fig_1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="figure 1"></a></p>
<figcaption>figure 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The choice of approximate posterior distribution is one of the core problems in variational inference. Most applications of variational inference employ simple families of posterior approximations in order to allow for efficient inference, focusing on mean-field or other simple structured approximations. This restriction has a significant impact on the quality of inferences made using variational methods. We introduce a new approach for specifying flexible, arbitrarily complex and scalable approximate posterior distributions. Our approximations are distributions constructed through a normalizing flow, whereby a simple initial density is transformed into a more complex one by applying a sequence of invertible transformations until a desired level of complexity is attained. We use this view of normalizing flows to develop categories of finite and infinitesimal flows and provide a unified view of approaches for constructing rich posterior approximations. We demonstrate that the theoretical advantages of having posteriors that better match the true posterior, combined with the scalability of amortized variational approaches, provides a clear improvement in performance and applicability of variational inference.</p>
<p>— <span class="citation" data-cites="rezende2016vinflows">(Rezende and Mohamed 2016)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-rezende2016vinflows" class="csl-entry">
Rezende, Danilo Jimenez, and Shakir Mohamed. 2016. <span>“Variational Inference with Normalizing Flows.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1505.05770">https://arxiv.org/abs/1505.05770</a>.
</div></div></div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./fig_2.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="figure 2"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/fig_2.png" class="col-page img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="figure 2"></a></p>
<figcaption>figure 2</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./alg_1.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="algorithm 1"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/alg_1.png" class="col-page img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="algorithm 1"></a></p>
<figcaption>algorithm 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./fig_3.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="figure 3"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/fig_3.png" class="col-page img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="figure 3"></a></p>
<figcaption>figure 3</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./table_1.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="table 1"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/table_1.png" class="col-page img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="table 1"></a></p>
<figcaption>table 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The Paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2022,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Variational {Inference} with {Normalizing} {Flows}},
  date = {2022-06-26},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2022. <span>“Variational Inference with Normalizing
Flows.”</span> June 26, 2022. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>variational inference</category>
  <category>normalizing flows</category>
  <category>probabilistic modeling</category>
  <category>stub</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2015/vi-with-normalizing-flows/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Skeletonization: A Technique for Trimming the Fat from a Network via Relevance Assessment</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1989/skeletonization/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>This Nips 1988 paper is about simplifying neural networks by removing redundant units. The authors’ approach is systematically identifying and removing redundant or less-relevant units without losing functionality.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./fig_1.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="figure 1"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1989/skeletonization/fig_1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="figure 1"></a></p>
<figcaption>figure 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="summary" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="mozer1988skeletonization">(Mozer and Smolensky 1988)</span> the authors presents a novel approach to simplifying neural networks by systematically identifying and removing redundant or less-relevant units. The authors address a key challenge in connectionist models: understanding and optimizing the network’s behavior by trimming unnecessary components without losing functionality.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-mozer1988skeletonization" class="csl-entry">
Mozer, Michael C, and Paul Smolensky. 1988. <span>“Skeletonization: A Technique for Trimming the Fat from a Network via Relevance Assessment.”</span> <em>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</em> 1.
</div></div><p>The core idea of the paper is to iteratively train a network, compute a relevance metric for each input or hidden unit, and eliminate the units that are least relevant to the network’s performance. The skeletonization process offers several practical benefits:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Constraining Generalization</strong>: By reducing redundant units, skeletonization effectively limits the network’s complexity, which can enhance its generalization capability.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Improving Learning Performance</strong>: Networks often require many hidden units to quickly learn a dataset. Skeletonization accelerates initial learning with excess units and trims unnecessary ones later, leading to better generalization without sacrificing learning speed.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Simplifying Network Behavior</strong>: The authors argue that skeletonization can transform complex networks into simpler models, effectively capturing core decision-making rules.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The technique contrasts with other approaches such as weight decay methods by opting for an all-or-none removal of units, motivated by the desire to identify the most critical components through explicit relevance metrics. These metrics are determined by computing the network’s error with and without specific units, using a time-averaged relevance estimate.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-contributions">Key Contributions</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Relevance Metric and Error Propagation</strong>: Mozer and Smolensky introduce a <mark>relevance measure derived from the network’s error response to the removal of a unit</mark>. The metric can be computed via an error propagation procedure similar to backpropagation, making the approach computationally feasible for larger networks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Practical Application in Simple Examples</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong>cue salience problem</strong>, the relevance metric highlights the most critical input unit, effectively eliminating irrelevant units.</li>
<li>In the <strong>rule-plus-exception problem</strong>, the method identifies the hidden unit responsible for most general cases, while distinguishing another unit that handles exceptions, reflecting the nuanced task structure.</li>
<li>The <strong>train problem</strong> demonstrates the technique’s ability to reduce inputs to a minimal set of features needed to differentiate categories.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Skeletonization in More Complex Tasks</strong>: Mozer and Smolensky apply skeletonization to more sophisticated problems like the <strong>four-bit multiplexor</strong> and the random mapping problem, showing that skeletonized networks can outperform standard ones in terms of both failure rate and learning speed.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="strengths" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strengths">Strengths</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Effective Reduction of Network Size</strong>: One of the most impressive outcomes is the ability of skeletonized networks to match or exceed the performance of larger networks with fewer units. The networks show resilience in maintaining their functionality even as units are removed.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Improvement in Learning Time</strong>: The authors provide evidence that learning with an initially large network and then trimming it can lead to faster convergence than training a smaller network from the start. This result challenges conventional thinking that fewer hidden units should always be preferable from the outset.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Rule Abstraction</strong>: The skeletonization process successfully identifies essential “rules” that govern network behavior, making it easier to interpret a network’s decisions in a simplified and concise manner.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="limitations-and-open-questions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="limitations-and-open-questions">Limitations and Open Questions</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Predefined Trimming Limit</strong>: One limitation of the paper’s approach is the need to predefine how much of the network to trim. While the authors acknowledge that magnitudes of relevance values may offer insights, an automatic stopping criterion based on these values is not fully explored.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Error Function Sensitivity</strong>: The paper highlights an issue with using quadratic error functions to compute relevance. The authors propose an alternative linear error function, but the sensitivity of results to different error metrics could benefit from further investigation.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Mozer and Smolensky’s skeletonization technique represents a significant step toward optimizing neural networks by removing redundant units without losing core functionality. The method not only improves learning performance but also offers valuable insights into the internal workings of neural networks. By focusing on relevance metrics, the authors pave the way for more interpretable, efficient, and generalized neural models.</p>
<p>Overall, skeletonization remains an influential contribution to the study of neural network optimization, providing both theoretical insights and practical improvements in learning systems.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The Paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2022,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Skeletonization: {A} {Technique} for {Trimming} the {Fat}
    from a {Network} via {Relevance} {Assessment}},
  date = {2022-06-22},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1989/skeletonization/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2022. <span>“Skeletonization: A Technique for Trimming
the Fat from a Network via Relevance Assessment.”</span> June 22, 2022.
<a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1989/skeletonization/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1989/skeletonization/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>neural networks</category>
  <category>pruning</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1989/skeletonization/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1989/skeletonization/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Simplifying Neural Networks by soft weight sharing</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1991/simplifing-NN-by-soft-weight-sharing/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This paper was mentioned in Geoffrey Hinton’s <a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/neural-networks-deep-learning/">Coursera course</a> as a way to simplify neural networks.</p>
<p>The main takeaway is that of modeling the loss using a mixture of Gaussians to cluster the weights and penalize the complexity of the model.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
To Dos
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ol type="1">
<li><label><input type="checkbox">add categories</label></li>
<li><label><input type="checkbox">add a citation for the course.</label></li>
<li><label><input type="checkbox">It would be worth-while to look through what he says about this paper if only to ensure the main result is made to stand out from some of the others.</label></li>
<li><label><input type="checkbox">Do a from scratch implementation of the paper</label></li>
<li><label><input type="checkbox">Do a Python implementation of the paper.</label></li>
<li><label><input type="checkbox">Why isn’t this technique easier to implement in practice?</label></li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>The primary aim of the paper <span class="citation" data-cites="nowlan2018simplifying">(Nowlan and Hinton 1992)</span> is reducing the complexity of neural networks by employing a mixture of Gaussian priors to the weights, creating a “soft” weight-sharing mechanism. Instead of simply penalizing large weights (as in L2 regularization), this method clusters the weights, allowing some to stay close to zero and others to remain non-zero, depending on their usefulness. Soft weight sharing along with weight decay, improving generalization and making the model more interpretable.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><mark>One way of simplifying neural networks so they generalize better is to add an extra term to the error function that will penalize complexity</mark>. Simple versions of this approach include penalizing the sum of the squares of the weights or penalizing the number of nonzero weights. We propose a more complicated penalty term in which the distribution of weight values is modeled as a mixture of multiple Gaussians. <mark>A set of weights is <em>simple</em> if the weights have high probability density under the mixture model</mark>. This can be achieved by clustering the weights into subsets with the weights in each cluster having very similar values. Since we do not know the appropriate means or variances of the clusters in advance, we allow the parameters of the mixture model to adapt at the same time as the network learns. Simulations on two different problems demonstrate that this complexity term is more effective than previous complexity terms</p>
<p>– <span class="citation" data-cites="nowlan2018simplifying">(Nowlan and Hinton 1992)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Weight clustering - a perplexing idea &amp; Other quandaries
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This notion of clustering weights is odd to say the least as these are just numbers in a data structure. Viewed as a method to reduce the effective number of parameters in the model, it makes some convoluted sense. What this idea seems to boil down to is that we are prioritizing neural net architectures with some abstract symmetry in the weights and thus a lower capacity and thus less prone to overfitting.</p>
<ul>
<li>We shall shall soon see that the authors have attempted to motivate this idea in at least two ways:
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Weight decay</strong> - the penalty is a function of the weights themselves based on <span class="citation" data-cites="plaut1986experiments">(Plaut, Nowlan, and Hinton 1986)</span></li>
<li><strong>A Bayesian perspective</strong> - is a negative log density of the weights under a Gaussian prior.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>it might also help if we learned that mixture models are often used to do clustering in unsupervised learning.</li>
</ul>
<p>A few quandaries then arise:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How can we figure for different layers having weights, gradients and learning rates being more correlated then between layers.</li>
<li>That there may be other structure so that the weights are not independent of each other.
<ol type="1">
<li>In classifiers the are continuous approximation of logic gates.</li>
<li>In regression settings their values approximate continuous variables ?</li>
</ol></li>
<li>In many networks most of the weights are in the last layer, so we can use a different penalty for the last layer.</li>
<li>Is there a way to impose an abstract symmetry on the weights of a neural network such that is commensurate with the problem?</li>
<li>Can we impose multiple such symmetries on the network to give it other advantages?
<ul>
<li>Invariance to certain transformations,</li>
<li>using it for initialization,</li>
<li>making the model more interpretable,</li>
<li>Once we learn these mixture distribution of weights, can we use its parameters in, batch normalization, layer norm and with other regularization techniques like dropout?</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></section>
<section id="the-problem" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-problem">The problem:</h2>
<p>This main problem in this paper is that of supervised ML</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>How to train a model so it will generalize well on unseen data?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In deep learning this problem is exacerbated by the fact that neural networks require fitting lots of parameters while the data for training is limited. This naturally leads to overfitting - memorizing the data and noise rather than learning the underlying data generating process.</p>
</section>
<section id="related-work" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-work">Related work</h2>
<p>How have others tried to solve this problem?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Weight Sharing</strong>: Reducing effective numbers of <em>free</em> parameters in a neural network by using a prior distribution over the weights. This is equivalent to adding a penalty term to the loss function. c.f. <span class="citation" data-cites="lang1990time">(Lang, Waibel, and Hinton 1990)</span></li>
<li><strong>Early Stopping</strong>: Does not restricts the parameters instead detecting the point when training and test scores diverge and stopping the training early. In reality weights are saved after each epoch and once we are certain that a divergence in say accuracy we restore the earlier weights c.f. <span class="citation" data-cites="morgan1989generalization">(Morgan and Bourlard 1989)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="weigend1990predicting">(Weigend, Huberman, and Rumelhart 1990)</span>.</li>
<li><strong>Pruning</strong>: Removing weight from the network <span class="citation" data-cites="mozer1989using">(Mozer and Smolensky 1989)</span>,
<ol type="1">
<li>keep track of the importance of each unit and drop the least important ones - could work well in RL where we keep track of the importance of each state/action/features we might also care more about prioritizing certain states and discarding others. c.f. <span class="citation" data-cites="mozer1989using">(Mozer and Smolensky 1989)</span></li>
<li>Use second order gradient information to estimate network sensitivity to weight changes and prune based on that. c.f. <span class="citation" data-cites="lecun-90b">(LeCun et al. 1990)</span></li>
</ol></li>
<li><strong>Penalty Term</strong>: Adding a term in the loss penelizing for the network’s complexity. c.f. <span class="citation" data-cites="mozer1989using">(Mozer and Smolensky 1989)</span> <span class="citation" data-cites="lecun-90b">(LeCun et al. 1990)</span><sup>1</sup>.
<ol type="1">
<li>Complexity can be approximated using sum of the squares of the weights.</li>
<li>Differentiating the sum of the squares of the weights leads to weight decay. <span class="citation" data-cites="plaut1986experiments">(Plaut, Nowlan, and Hinton 1986)</span></li>
</ol></li>
</ul>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-lang1990time" class="csl-entry">
Lang, Kevin J, Alex H Waibel, and Geoffrey E Hinton. 1990. <span>“A Time-Delay Neural Network Architecture for Isolated Word Recognition.”</span> <em>Neural Networks</em> 3 (1): 23–43.
</div><div id="ref-morgan1989generalization" class="csl-entry">
Morgan, Nelson, and Hervé Bourlard. 1989. <span>“Generalization and Parameter Estimation in Feedforward Nets: Some Experiments.”</span> <em>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</em> 2.
</div><div id="ref-weigend1990predicting" class="csl-entry">
Weigend, Andreas S, Bernardo A Huberman, and David E Rumelhart. 1990. <span>“Predicting the Future: A Connectionist Approach.”</span> <em>International Journal of Neural Systems</em> 1 (03): 193–209.
</div><div id="ref-mozer1989using" class="csl-entry">
Mozer, Michael C, and Paul Smolensky. 1989. <span>“Using Relevance to Reduce Network Size Automatically.”</span> <em>Connection Science</em> 1 (1): 3–16.
</div><div id="ref-lecun-90b" class="csl-entry">
LeCun, Yann, J. S. Denker, S. Solla, R. E. Howard, and L. D. Jackel. 1990. <span>“Optimal Brain Damage.”</span> In <em>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 1989)</em>, edited by David Touretzky. Vol. 2. Denver, CO: Morgan Kaufman. <a href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper_files/paper/1989/file/6c9882bbac1c7093bd25041881277658-Paper.pdf">https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper_files/paper/1989/file/6c9882bbac1c7093bd25041881277658-Paper.pdf</a>.
</div><div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;in the paper this citation is ambiguous, but I think this is the correct one - based on the abstract</p></div><div id="ref-nowlan2018simplifying" class="csl-entry">
Nowlan, Steven J., and Geoffrey E. Hinton. 1992. <span>“<span class="nocase">Simplifying Neural Networks by Soft Weight-Sharing</span>.”</span> <em>Neural Computation</em> 4 (4): 473–93. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/neco.1992.4.4.473">https://doi.org/10.1162/neco.1992.4.4.473</a>.
</div></div><p>Just a few ideas from this paper: <span class="citation" data-cites="nowlan2018simplifying">(Nowlan and Hinton 1992)</span></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7Bcost%7D%20=%20%5Ctext%7Bdata-misfit%7D%20+%20%5Clambda%20%5Ctimes%20%5Ctext%7Bcomplexity%7D%20%5Cqquad%0A"></p>
<p>penalties:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20w_i%5E2%20%5Cqquad%20%5Ctext%7B(L2%20penalty)%7D%0A"></p>
<p>the authors provide two ways to think about this penalty:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Weight decay</strong> - the penalty is a function of the weights themselves based on <span class="citation" data-cites="plaut1986experiments">(Plaut, Nowlan, and Hinton 1986)</span></li>
<li><strong>a Bayesian perspective</strong> - is a negative log density of the weights under a Gaussian prior.</li>
</ol>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-plaut1986experiments" class="csl-entry">
Plaut, D. C., S. J. Nowlan, and G. E. Hinton. 1986. <span>“Experiments on Learning by Back-Propagation.”</span> CMU-CS-86-126. Pittsburgh, PA: Carnegie–Mellon University. <a href="https://ni.cmu.edu/~plaut/papers/pdf/PlautNowlanHinton86TR.backprop.pdf">https://ni.cmu.edu/~plaut/papers/pdf/PlautNowlanHinton86TR.backprop.pdf</a>.
</div></div><p>The authors point out that the problem with L2 penalty term is that it prefers two weak interactions over a strong one.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cleft(%5Cfrac%7Bw%7D%7B2%7D%5Cright)%5E2+%5Cleft(%5Cfrac%7Bw%7D%7B2%7D%5Cright)%5E2%20%3C%20w%5E2%20+%200%20%5Cqquad%0A"></p>
<p>we want to keep larger weights and drop the smaller ones</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ap(w)%20=%20%5Cpi_n%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%20%5Cpi%5Csigma_n%7De%5E%7B-w%5E2/2%5Csigma%5E2_n%7D%20+%20%5Cpi_b%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%20%5Cpi%5Csigma_b%7De%5E%7B-w%5E2/2%5Csigma%5E2_b%7D%20%5Cqquad%0A"></p>
<p>This is equivalent to the L2 penalty. <span class="citation" data-cites="mackay1991bayesian">(MacKay 1991)</span> showed that we can do better with:</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-mackay1991bayesian" class="csl-entry">
MacKay, David JC. 1991. <span>“Bayesian Modeling and Neural Networks.”</span> <em>PhD Thesis, Dept. Of Computation and Neural Systems, CalTech</em>. <a href="https://www.inference.org.uk/mackay/thesis.pdf">https://www.inference.org.uk/mackay/thesis.pdf</a>.
</div></div><p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ap(w)%20=%5Csum_i%20%5Clambda_i%20%5Csum_%7Bj%7D%20w_j%5E2%20%5Cqquad%20%5Ctext%7B(L2%20penalty)%7D%0A"></p>
<p>where</p>
<ul>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?i"> is the layer and</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?j"> is the weight in that layer</li>
</ul>
<p>Different layers has a different penalty, which is equivalent to a Gaussian prior with different variances for each layer.<sup>2</sup></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;note: this answers the first of my question above.</p></div></div><p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20%5Cdelta(w%7B_i%5Cne%200%7D)%20%5Cqquad%20%5Ctext%7B(L0%20penalty)%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ap(w)%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20%5Cdelta(w_i%20%5Cne%200)%20+%20%5Clambda%20%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20w_i%5E2%0A"></p>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="resources">Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li>Article <a href="https://machinelearningmastery.com/introduction-to-weight-constraints-to-reduce-generalization-error-in-deep-learning/">using weight constraints to reduce generalization</a></li>
<li>The paper is available at https://www.cs.utoronto.ca/~hinton/absps/sunspots.pdf</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="an-after-thought" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-after-thought">An after thought</h2>
<p>Can we use a Bayesian RL to tune the hyper-parameters of model and dataset. We can perhaps create an RL alg that controls the many aspects of training of a model. It can explore/exploit different setups on subsets of the data. Find variants that converge faster and are more robust by adding constraints at different levels. It can identify problems in the datasets (possible bad labels etc) . Ensambles, mixtures of experts, different regularization strategies. Different Learning rates and schedules globaly or per layer.</p>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2022,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Simplifying {Neural} {Networks} by Soft Weight Sharing},
  date = {2022-06-22},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1991/simplifing-NN-by-soft-weight-sharing/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2022. <span>“Simplifying Neural Networks by Soft Weight
Sharing.”</span> June 22, 2022. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1991/simplifing-NN-by-soft-weight-sharing/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1991/simplifing-NN-by-soft-weight-sharing/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>neural networks</category>
  <category>regularization</category>
  <category>stub</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/1991/simplifing-NN-by-soft-weight-sharing/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>VGGNet: Very Deep Convolutional Networks for Large-Scale Image Recognition</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>In this paper <span class="citation" data-cites="simonyan2015deepconvolutionalnetworkslargescale">(Simonyan and Zisserman 2015)</span> the authors, Karen Simonyan and Andrew Zisserman from the Visual Geometry Group at Oxford, investigated the effect of increasing the convolutional network depth on the accuracy in the large-scale image recognition setting. The authors show that a significant improvement on the prior-art configurations can be achieved by pushing the depth to 16-19 weight layers.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><ul>
<li><p>By using 3x3 convolution filters with stride of 1 instead of larger ones like 5x5 or 7x7 the authors were able to reduce the number of parameters in the network which allowed them to use deeper networks (16-19) layers with a similar capacity to earlier networks. This is possible as stack of three 3x3 convolutional layers has an effective receptive field of 7x7 with 81% fewer parameters than a single 7x7 convolutional layer. Once this was understood 3x3 became the standard convolutional filter size in modern CNN architectures.</p></li>
<li><p>The authors introduced a data augmentation method called ‘image jittering’ which varying image scales.</p></li>
<li><p>The authors later tweaked their model further including using 1x1 convolutional layers and Local Response Normalization (LRN) which improved the performance of the model as well as Xaiver initialization. And they were able to achieve state-of-the-art results on the ImageNet dataset.</p></li>
<li><p>The authors released weights for <strong>VGG16</strong> and <strong>VGG19</strong> Called D and E in the table below which were the basis of their ImageNet Challenge 2014 submission. And it is is these two models that are most commonly used in practice as thier weight are available in the Keras library <span class="citation" data-cites="chollet2015keras">(Chollet et al. 2015)</span>.</p></li>
</ul>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-chollet2015keras" class="csl-entry">
Chollet, François et al. 2015. <span>“Keras.”</span> <a href="https://keras.io" class="uri">https://keras.io</a>.
</div></div></section>
<section id="the-abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-abstract">The abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In this work <mark>we investigate the effect of the convolutional network depth on its accuracy</mark> in the large-scale image recognition setting. Our main contribution is a thorough evaluation of networks of increasing depth using an architecture with very small (3x3) convolution filters, which shows that a <mark>significant improvement on the prior-art configurations can be achieved by pushing the depth to 16-19 weight layers</mark>. These findings were the basis of our ImageNet Challenge 2014 submission, where our team secured the first and the second places in the localisation and classification tracks respectively. We also show that our representations generalise well to other datasets, where they achieve state-of-the-art results. We have made our two best-performing ConvNet models publicly available to facilitate further research on the use of deep visual representations in computer vision. — <span class="citation" data-cites="simonyan2015deepconvolutionalnetworkslargescale">(Simonyan and Zisserman 2015)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-simonyan2015deepconvolutionalnetworkslargescale" class="csl-entry">
Simonyan, Karen, and Andrew Zisserman. 2015. <span>“Very Deep Convolutional Networks for Large-Scale Image Recognition.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.1556">https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.1556</a>.
</div></div></div>
</section>
<section id="review" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h2>
<p>The paper has a table with some network architectures and their performance on the ImageNet dataset. In many cases data scientist etc. like to copy the architectures of well known models and use them in their own work. So this paper is a good reference for giving a few more options for architectures to use.</p>
<p>The paper uses 3x3 convolution filters which is a common practice in modern CNN architectures.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We use very small 3 × 3 receptive fields throughout the whole net, which are convolved with the input at every pixel (with stride 1). It is easy to see that a stack of two 3 × 3 conv. layers (without spatial pooling in between) has an effective receptive field of 5 × 5; three such layers have a 7 × 7 effective receptive field. <mark>So what have we gained by using, for instance, a stack of three 3 × 3 conv. layers instead of a single 7 × 7 layer? First, we incorporate three non-linear rectification layers instead of a single one, which makes the decision function more discriminative. Second, we decrease the number of parameters</mark>: assuming that both the input and the output of a three-layer 3 × 3 convolution stack has C channels, the stack is parametrised by 3 (32C2) = 27C^2 weights; at the same time, a single 7 × 7 conv. layer would require 72C2 = 49C2 parameters, i.e.&nbsp;81% more. This can be seen as imposing a regularisation on the 7 × 7 conv. filters, forcing them to have a decomposition through the 3 × 3 filters (with non-linearity injected in between).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The authors also reference 1 × 1 convolutions from [NiN] paper which also have large FC layers at the end.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./table1.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="architecture"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/table1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="architecture"></a></p>
<figcaption>architecture</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Where: - A is 11 layered. - A-LRN is 11 layered but have Local Response Normalization. - B is 13 layered. - C is 16 layered but has 1x1 convolutional layers. - D is 16 layered but 1x1 convolutional layers in C are replaced with 3x3 convolutional layers. - E is 19 layered</p>
<p>Training</p>
<p>The result were state of the art but by 2018 <span class="citation" data-cites="DBLP:journals/corr/GoyalDGNWKTJH17">(Goyal et al. 2017)</span> it would be possible to train a ResNet-50 imagenet classifier in under an hour of compute with just using 256 GPUs. There is little novelty in the methods. The authors simply increased the depth of the network and increase the umber of parameters.(but they also used them more efficiently).</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-DBLP:journals/corr/GoyalDGNWKTJH17" class="csl-entry">
Goyal, Priya, Piotr Dollár, Ross B. Girshick, Pieter Noordhuis, Lukasz Wesolowski, Aapo Kyrola, Andrew Tulloch, Yangqing Jia, and Kaiming He. 2017. <span>“Accurate, Large Minibatch <span>SGD:</span> Training ImageNet in 1 Hour.”</span> <em>CoRR</em> abs/1706.02677. <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1706.02677">http://arxiv.org/abs/1706.02677</a>.
</div><div id="ref-BibEntry2024Sep" class="csl-entry">
Appalapuri, Prabhu. 2016. <span>“<span class="nocase">Very-Deep-Convolutional-Networks-for-Large-Scale-Image-Recognition</span>.”</span> <a href="https://github.com/Prabhu204/Very-Deep-Convolutional-Networks-for-Large-Scale-Image-Recognition" class="uri">https://github.com/Prabhu204/Very-Deep-Convolutional-Networks-for-Large-Scale-Image-Recognition</a>; GitHub.
</div></div><p>At <span class="citation" data-cites="BibEntry2024Sep">(Appalapuri 2016)</span> I found a Pytorch implementation of this paper.</p>
<p>Many People ask what is the difference between VGG16 and VGG19. The difference is that VGG19 has 3 more convolutional layers than VGG16. Since these extra convolutional layers are stacked after two other layers, the receptive field of VGG19 is larger than that of VGG16. Also the CNN also have a RELU so that the network also has increased discriminative power. This means that VGG19 can capture more complex patterns in the input image than VGG16. However, this comes at the cost of more parameters and more computation. In practice, VGG16 is often used because it is simpler and faster to train than VGG19.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./vgg16.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="VGG16"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/vgg16.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="VGG16"></a></p>
<figcaption>VGG16</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./vgg19.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="VGG19"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/vgg19.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="800" alt="VGG19"></a></p>
<figcaption>VGG19</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!--
::: callout-warning

:::: {.column-margin}

![](captain_abvious.jpg){width="250px"} 




@meme2013captainobvious

> More layers $\implies$ more parameters <br>
> more parameters $\implies$ more capacity <br>
> more capacity $\implies$ better fit. <br>
> BaZinga! 🚀

::::

It seems that the authors were aware of methods for speeding up training but they did not bother with them. They as using 4 GPUs gave them the results in 2-3 weeks per model.

:::
-->
</section>
<section id="limitations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="limitations">Limitations</h2>
<ul>
<li>The authors did not use any data augmentation methods like random cropping, flipping, etc. which are common in modern CNN architectures. They also did not use any regularization methods like dropout, L2 regularization, etc. which are also common in modern CNN architectures.</li>
<li>The networks are pretty massive and require a lot of GPU memory in inference.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="resources">Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.robots.ox.ac.uk/~vgg/research/very_deep/">home page</a></li>
<li>https://medium.com/<span class="citation" data-cites="siddheshb008/vgg-net-architecture-explained-71179310050f">(<strong>siddheshb008/vgg-net-architecture-explained-71179310050f?</strong>)</span></li>
<li>https://karan3-zoh.medium.com/paper-summary-very-deep-convolutional-networks-for-large-scale-image-recognition-e7437959d856</li>
<li>https://safakkbilici.github.io/summary-vggnet/</li>
<li>https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~frossard/post/vgg16/</li>
</ul>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman2015,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {VGGNet: {Very} {Deep} {Convolutional} {Networks} for
    {Large-Scale} {Image} {Recognition}},
  date = {2015-12-10},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman2015" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. 2015. <span>“VGGNet: Very Deep Convolutional Networks for
Large-Scale Image Recognition.”</span> December 10, 2015. <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2014/VGGNet/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Evolution of Coding in signaling games</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
TL;DR: The Evolution of Coding in signaling games
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="../../../images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="The Evolution of Coding In a Nutshell"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/images/in_the_nut_shell_coach_retouched.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The Evolution of Coding In a Nutshell"></a></p>
<figcaption>The Evolution of Coding In a Nutshell</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This paper considers a setting for the evolution of a complex signaling systems</p>
<ul>
<li>in this case social evolution or reinforcement learning. As I have already implemented such a system based on Skyrym’s work I was interested in the results. I think this is one of the papers discussed in the book by Skyrms. The main contribution is an extension of the Lewis signaling game of multiple senders that send partial binary signals to the receiver. The receiver aggregates these into a sequence ordered by sender. A complex signaling system is thus learned in which senders spontaneously learn to send a specific partial state.</li>
</ul>
<p>It may seem surprising that the senders learn to coordinate what part of the state to send even though they start out by picking the signals to send independently of each other.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Signaling games with reinforcement learning have been used to model the evolution of term languages (<span class="citation" data-cites="lewis1969convention">(<strong>lewis1969convention?</strong>)</span>; <span class="citation" data-cites="skyrms2010signals">(<strong>skyrms2010signals?</strong>)</span>). In this article, syntactic games, extensions of David Lewis’s original sender–receiver game, are used to illustrate how a language that exploits available syntactic structure might evolve to code for states of the world. The evolution of a language occurs in the context of available vocabulary and syntax—the role played by each component is compared in the context of simple reinforcement learning</p>
<p>– <span class="citation" data-cites="barrett2009evolution">(<strong>barrett2009evolution?</strong>)</span></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="the-review" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-review">The Review</h2>
<p>First the Lewis signaling game is explained - the game is not presented in terms of game theory e.g.&nbsp;it’s extensive form but using a state transition diagram.</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fig-1" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored" data-group="figures">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-1-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="./fig_1.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="figures" title="Figure&nbsp;1: Lewis signaling game"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/fig_1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-1-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: Lewis signaling game
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div><p>Later lewis signaling variant with two senders is introduced</p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fig-2" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored" data-group="figures">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-2-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="./fig_2.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="figures" title="Figure&nbsp;2: two sender Lewis signaling game"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/fig_2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-2-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: two sender Lewis signaling game
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div><p>The paper starts with the standard Lewis signaling game a metric for signaling success a few learning algorithms</p>
<ul>
<li>Urn Model after Richard Herrnstein’s matching law and with Rewards := {Succ: +1, Fail:0}</li>
<li>Urn Model after Richard Herrnstein’s matching law and with Rewards := {Succ: +2, Fail:-1} AKA ARP model</li>
<li>Bereby-Meyer and Erev 1998 “On learning to become a successful loser”</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Better RL Models
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The Herrnstein’s matching law <span class="citation" data-cites="Herrnstein1961Reinforcement">(Herrnstein 1961)</span> is not a well suited to learning in the signaling system. It is not sample efficient (e.g.&nbsp;it does not learn from making mistakes thus most of the samples are discarded) nor can it escape form the numerous attraction basins of the (partial) pooling equilibria which represent local maxima of expected returns to locate the much rarer global maxima of the separating equilibria that we call signaling systems.</p>
<p>Thus the authors looked for algorithms that could converge faster and also overcome the attraction basins due to local minima of the partial pooling equilibria. Some alternatives listed by Skyrms in <span class="citation" data-cites="skyrms2010signals">(<strong>skyrms2010signals?</strong>)</span> are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Thorndike’s law of effect (<span class="citation" data-cites="Thorndike1927LawOfEffect">Thorndike (1927)</span>)</li>
<li>Richard Herrnstein’s matching law (<span class="citation" data-cites="Herrnstein1961Reinforcement">Herrnstein (1961)</span>)</li>
<li>Roth-Erev learning algorithm <span class="citation" data-cites="RothErev1995Learning">(<strong>RothErev1995Learning?</strong>)</span></li>
<li>Bush–Mosteller Reinforcement <span class="citation" data-cites="bush1953stochastic">(<strong>bush1953stochastic?</strong>)</span> Has been shown to correspond the replicator dynamics in the limit of small learning rates.</li>
<li>Yoella Bereby-Meyer and Ido Erev ARP model <span class="citation" data-cites="Bereby1998Loser">(<strong>Bereby1998Loser?</strong>)</span></li>
</ul>
<p>This paper looks at a variant of the Roth-Erev learning which was published in <span class="citation" data-cites="Bereby1998Loser">(<strong>Bereby1998Loser?</strong>)</span> by Bereby-Meyer and Erev titled “On Learning To Become a Successful Loser”. Here the authors consider different abstraction of losses in repeated choice tasks. They use a probability learning task. (basically to estimate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p%5Cneq0.5"> in a Bernulli trial). They found that by adding constants to the payoff matrix enhanced the learning process and more significantly that learning in the loss domain was faster then in the gain domain.<sup>1</sup></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;there are many games where lossess are much more common, also we might not be able to get a signal from a mistake…. </p></div></div><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Herrnstein1961Reinforcement" class="csl-entry">
Herrnstein, R. J. 1961. <span>“RELATIVE AND ABSOLUTE STRENGTH OF RESPONSE AS a FUNCTION OF FREQUENCY OF REINFORCEMENT.”</span> <em>Journal of the Experimental Analysis of Behavior</em> 4 (3): 267–72. https://doi.org/<a href="https://doi.org/10.1901/jeab.1961.4-267">https://doi.org/10.1901/jeab.1961.4-267</a>.
</div></div><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Thorndike1927LawOfEffect" class="csl-entry">
Thorndike, Edward L. 1927. <span>“The Law of Effect.”</span> <em>The American Journal of Psychology</em> 39 (1/4): 212–22. <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1415413">http://www.jstor.org/stable/1415413</a>.
</div></div><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><pre><code>Bereby-Meyer and Erev</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>To my considerable surprise, Barrett found that Roth–Erev reinforcement learners reliably learned to optimally categorize and signal. — <span class="citation" data-cites="skyrms2010signals">(<strong>skyrms2010signals?</strong>)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
The Blind Watchmaker in the Lewis Signaling Game
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>In his popular science Classic “The blind watchmaker” <span class="citation" data-cites="dawkins1986the-blind-watch">(Dawkins 1986)</span>, the author, Richard Dawkins, suggest the notion of a blind watchmaker. The idea is that the blind watchmaker does not have to know how to make a watch rather he has to be able to learn by by trial and error how to make better watches. Given the millions of years, evolution’s blind watch maker seems to design wonders with much greater complexity than any watch.</p>
<p>The way I understand this ability to learn to coordinate is</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The senders don’t really learn to coordinate - we have a blind watchmaker at work here….</li>
<li>Initially Senders don’t really have any meaning in the Lewis signaling game. Only when the environment assign a positive reward (which is a spontaneous symmetry breaking event) due to the a receiver taking the correct action. At this point the senders are bound to send the same signals they each sent before. That is the convention they are learning.</li>
<li>Assuming they won’t use the same signal combinations again for a different state, this is repeated until all the states and signals are learned.</li>
<li>There is no reason for the senders to send the same part of the state - they could alternate.</li>
</ol>
<p>2 signaling systems for a 4 by 4 game</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<caption>a SS with correlated senders and sub-state</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>state</th>
<th>sender 1</th>
<th>sender 2</th>
<th>receiver</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>0,0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0,0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>0,1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0,1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1,0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1,1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>1,1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1,0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table class="caption-top table">
<caption>a SS with un-correlated senders and sub-state</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>state</th>
<th>sender 1</th>
<th>sender 2</th>
<th>receiver</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>0,1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0,1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>1,0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1,1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>0,0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0,0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>1,1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1,0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>For sender 1 and sender 2 any mapping of the signals to state that is one to one works.</p>
<p>However in terms of learnability a system that has a correlated sender sub-state assignment is easier to learn. Is easier to learn because the receiver can learn the mapping of the signals to the state in a single step.</p>
<p>To sum up: senders are assigned a one to one mapping spontaneously whenever the receiver takes the correct action. If they are de correlated with each other or correlated with a sub-state is not important.</p>
<p>However we can see that an arbitrary assignment of the signals to the state is harder to learn. This is because the receiver has to learn the full mapping of the signals to the state. Whereas in the correlated case the receiver can reuse the mapping to generalize.</p>
<p>Note: here we assume that the agents consider the signaling system as mappings rather than a dictionary.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-dawkins1986the-blind-watch" class="csl-entry">
Dawkins, R. 1986. <em>The Blind Watchmaker</em>. Longman Scientific; Technical.
</div></div><p>Criticism:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The new game is not considered from a game theoretic point of view.
<ul>
<li>The extensive form should be made clear.</li>
<li>We don’t have just a new sender - we have seperate information sets for each sender. In RL the senders and the recievers all have different partial information corersponding to a highly localized view of the world.</li>
<li>Senders don’t see each others signals - as if they must signal at the same time.</li>
<li>We don’t know if it has similar equilibria as the lewis signaling game.</li>
<li>We don’t now if there are new kinds of equilibria.</li>
<li>We don’t know how they are distributed neumerically and this has bearing on the many tables shown in the paper. i.e.&nbsp;do the different empirical rates of success reflect what is expected in term of the relative numbers of equilibria in the game.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The algorithms used in the paper do not learn to categorically exclude pooling equilibria. So they are slow to converge. Nor do they learn to exclude already solved state action pairs. This makes them slow to converge.</li>
<li>When the initial distribution of signals is not uniform the agents should do better not worse as they should learn a coding that is more efficient. This notion of coding is mentioned in the paper’s title but we don’t get a satisfying result. Perhaps there is a better way to learn efficient coding for a signaling system.</li>
</ol>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
My Research questions:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Two approaches to the signaling system</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>sender and receiver create the system spontaneously.</li>
<li>sender envisions a signaling system, and receiver needs to learn it. There is just one correct signaling system.</li>
<li>there are many systems and agents coordinate via a beliefs to exclude non-optimal systems.
<ul>
<li>this is better because it can handle the case where two groups of agents have learned similar systems and the best common system should emerege.</li>
<li>case when the sender dies by predation and is replaced by a new sender.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>how do we learn to coordinate without pooling equilibria?
<ul>
<li>hint: excluding already solved state action pairs.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>how fast should a data efficient algorithm converge to a signaling system?
<ul>
<li>hint: like a coupon collector problem a sum of negative binomials gives <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?O(n%20log%20n)"></li>
</ul></li>
<li>how can do better?
<ul>
<li>as succsses are very rare early on using negative rewards for failure can speed up learning.</li>
<li>using multiple learners can further improve convergence.</li>
<li>using source coding should help if the states are not uniformly distributed</li>
</ul></li>
<li>how can we learn the most salient signaling system for an uneven distribution of states possibly changing over time?
<ul>
<li>hint: if the urn model is directly learning the mapping this may be hard</li>
<li>hint: consider an urn scheme that votes via a belief on the most salient signaling system.
<ul>
<li>this would let the agents switch between signaling systems as the distribution of states changes. What is the overhead?</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>The book by Skryms suggests that different types of aggregations may lead to different signaling systems. He point out that conjunction is less powerful than concatenation.
<ul>
<li>I Found that implementing different aggregation schemes can be challenging - particularly if one has not read this paper! In fact it is hard enough to come up with variants for hard coded aggregation schemes for just the two cases above.
<ul>
<li>hint: using a FSM requries coordinating on some matrix of transitions.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>If one thinks of the desiderata for coding schemes - they should be easy to learn, easy to extend, easy to decode, and robust to errors. The easy to decode is also disrable here. I think that aggregation schemes are not very different from coding schemes once we have the ability to handle a sequence of signals.</li>
<li>Another complexity is that we could consider different settings like in RL. Here if we follow the book, we have
<ul>
<li>single sender single receiver (Lewis game)</li>
<li>multiple senders each with a disjoint partially state and a single receiver (leads to conjunctive aggregations to recover the state)</li>
<li>constrained binary signal and single receiver (full observability solves the sender decorolated coordination problem - that senders send different parts of the state)</li>
<li>multiple senders with a fully observed state</li>
</ul></li>
<li>In reality there is a whole zoo of aggregation schemes that are in use in natural languages.
<ul>
<li>template based aggregation for template based grammar and morphology (sequence of t signals)</li>
<li>tree based aggregation leading to recursive structures.</li>
<li>conjunctive aggregation for logical inference.
<ul>
<li>hint operators with noop symbol for closing implied bracket</li>
<li>sequence with nary operator + &gt; to close the context.
<ul>
<li>and ( A, B or C , D ) =&gt; and_n A or_n B C &gt; D &gt;</li>
</ul></li>
<li>encoding treess elegently using nary prefix operators
<ul>
<li>and ( A, B or C , D ) =&gt; and_3 A or2 B C D</li>
</ul></li>
<li>operators take arity as thier first argument like
<ul>
<li>and ( A, B or C , D ) =&gt; and 3 A or 2 B C D this can implement run length encoding too using</li>
<li>RLENC arity repetition input+ 0 1 2 3</li>
<li>and (aaabb aaabb aaabb) =&gt; RLENC 3 3 RLENC 3 3 a RLENC 3 2 b</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>The issue here is that the aggregation scheme is not learned but fixed. If we were able to also learn an agreagation scheme we might understand how morphology, syntax and many other features of language emerge from a simple aggregation rule.</li>
<li>How can we learn the most efficient aggregation for a signaling system?</li>
<li>hint: using a template for the aggregation may be more efficient than learning the aggregation from scratch.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {The {Evolution} of {Coding} in Signaling Games},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. n.d. <span>“The Evolution of Coding in Signaling
Games.”</span> <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>review</category>
  <category>reinforcement learning</category>
  <category>signaling games</category>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:01:47 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2007/evolution_of_coding/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Multi-column Deep Neural Networks for Image Classification</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/Multi-column deep neural networks for image classi cation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="cireşan2012multicolumndeepneuralnetworks">(Cireşan, Meier, and Schmidhuber 2012)</span> titled “Multi-column Deep Neural Networks for Image Classification”, the authors, Dan Cireşan, Ueli Meier, Juergen Schmidhuber introduce a biologically plausible deep artificial neural network architecture that achieves near-human performance on tasks such as the recognition of handwritten digits or traffic signs. The method uses small receptive fields of convolutional winner-take-all neurons to yield large network depth, resulting in roughly as many sparsely connected neural layers as found in mammals between retina and visual cortex. The authors demonstrate that their approach outperforms humans on a traffic sign recognition benchmark and improves the state-of-the-art on various image classification benchmarks.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Traditional methods of computer vision and machine learning cannot match human performance on tasks such as the recognition of handwritten digits or traffic signs. Our biologically plausible deep artificial neural network architectures can. Small (often minimal) receptive fields of convolutional winner-take-all neurons yield large network depth, resulting in roughly as many sparsely connected neural layers as found in mammals between retina and visual cortex. Only winner neurons are trained. Several deep neural columns become experts on inputs preprocessed in different ways; their predictions are averaged. Graphics cards allow for fast training. On the very competitive MNIST handwriting benchmark, our method is the first to achieve near-human performance. On a traffic sign recognition benchmark it outperforms humans by a factor of two. We also improve the state-of-the-art on a plethora of common image classification benchmarks. — <span class="citation" data-cites="cireşan2012multicolumndeepneuralnetworks">(Cireşan, Meier, and Schmidhuber 2012)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></div>
</section>
<section id="review" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h2>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="cireşan2012multicolumndeepneuralnetworks">(Cireşan, Meier, and Schmidhuber 2012)</span> the authors make significant strides in the field of image classification by demonstrating the effectiveness of multi-column deep neural networks (DNNs). <mark>This work is noteworthy for its pioneering approach in applying deep learning techniques to image classification tasks, which have since become the foundation of modern computer vision systems.</mark></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-cireşan2012multicolumndeepneuralnetworks" class="csl-entry">
Cireşan, Dan, Ueli Meier, and Juergen Schmidhuber. 2012. <span>“Multi-Column Deep Neural Networks for Image Classification.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1202.2745">https://arxiv.org/abs/1202.2745</a>.
</div></div></section>
<section id="key-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-contributions">Key Contributions</h2>
<p>The authors present a system that uses several deep neural networks, each operating as a “column,” which are trained independently. The outputs of these networks are then averaged to form the final prediction. This multi-column approach exploits the diversity between different networks and boosts classification accuracy, reducing the impact of overfitting and improving generalization. Notably, the method achieved state-of-the-art results on several image classification benchmarks at the time, including the MNIST digit recognition task.</p>
<p>One of the central contributions of this paper is the demonstration of how <mark>combining multiple deep networks can outperform single networks in complex image classification tasks</mark>. The authors trained their models on NVIDIA GPUs, which allowed them to scale deep networks efficiently—a relatively new practice when this paper was published, underscoring its innovative edge.</p>
</section>
<section id="strengths" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strengths">Strengths</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Improvement on Benchmarks</strong>: The multi-column DNN approach delivered unprecedented accuracy on datasets like MNIST, achieving an error rate of just 0.23%. This represents one of the early breakthroughs that paved the way for deep learning in computer vision.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Effective Use of Parallelism</strong>: The paper highlights the use of modern GPUs to efficiently train deep networks, illustrating how hardware advancements can accelerate research progress.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Generalizability</strong>: While the paper focuses on MNIST and other datasets, the multi-column DNN framework offers a flexible approach to other image classification tasks. The general architecture and training methodology could be adapted to more complex datasets, making this work highly relevant across a variety of image recognition problems.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Robustness</strong>: By averaging outputs from multiple networks, the system reduces the sensitivity to the specific architecture or initialization of a single network. This ensemble-like approach increases robustness and reduces error rates.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="weaknesses" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weaknesses">Weaknesses</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Lack of Theoretical Insight</strong>: Although the empirical results are impressive, the paper does not delve deeply into the theoretical reasons behind the success of multi-column architectures. It remains unclear how much of the performance gain is due to ensembling versus the intrinsic strength of the individual networks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Computational Cost</strong>: The approach requires training multiple deep neural networks independently, which could be computationally expensive for larger datasets or higher-dimensional inputs. While GPUs mitigate this to an extent, scaling the multi-column approach to larger tasks would demand significant computational resources.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Limited Applicability to Other Modalities</strong>: The paper focuses solely on image classification. While it hints at the potential for multi-column networks in other domains (e.g., audio or text), the paper doesn’t explore these extensions or provide empirical evidence beyond the image domain.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="impact-and-relevance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="impact-and-relevance">Impact and Relevance</h2>
<p>This paper marked a turning point for deep learning in computer vision, showing the power of combining deep networks for complex tasks like image classification. Its success on benchmarks like MNIST helped popularize deep learning as a dominant method for pattern recognition and set the stage for more advanced techniques. Although it primarily focuses on image classification, the insights regarding ensemble learning through independent deep networks have since inspired various approaches in different machine learning areas, including speech recognition and natural language processing.</p>
<p>The paper is particularly significant when viewed in the context of its time (2012), as it predated the massive adoption of deep learning across industries. Its methods were fundamental to later developments in deep convolutional neural networks, which have become a cornerstone of state-of-the-art models in computer vision tasks today.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Ciresan, Meier, and Schmidhuber’s work on multi-column deep neural networks represents a crucial step forward in the development of image classification techniques. Its impact on deep learning, especially in terms of model ensembling and parallelization using GPUs, cannot be overstated. While it comes with some computational challenges and lacks deep theoretical explanation, the paper’s practical results and novel approach have solidified its place as a landmark contribution in the history of deep learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Multi-Column {Deep} {Neural} {Networks} for {Image}
    {Classification}},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/Multi-column deep neural networks for image classi cation/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. n.d. <span>“Multi-Column Deep Neural Networks for Image
Classification.”</span> <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/Multi-column deep neural networks for image classi cation/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/Multi-column
deep neural networks for image classi cation/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/Multi-column deep neural networks for image classi cation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:01:47 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/Multi-column deep neural networks for image classi cation/cover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Improving Neural Networks by Preventing Co-Adaptation of Feature Detectors</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/dropout/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="hinton2012improvingneuralnetworkspreventing">(Hinton et al. 2012)</span> titled “Improving Neural Networks by Preventing Co-Adaptation of Feature Detectors”, the authors, Hinton, Geoffrey E., Nitish Srivastava, Alex Krizhevsky, Ilya Sutskever, and Ruslan R. Salakhutdinov introduces a new regularization technique called “Dropout” that helps to prevent overfitting in neural networks. Dropout is a simple and effective way to improve the performance of neural networks by preventing co-adaptation of feature detectors. The authors show that dropout can be used to improve the performance of a wide range of neural networks, including deep networks, convolutional networks, and recurrent networks.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-hinton2012improvingneuralnetworkspreventing" class="csl-entry">
Hinton, Geoffrey E., Nitish Srivastava, Alex Krizhevsky, Ilya Sutskever, and Ruslan R. Salakhutdinov. 2012. <span>“Improving Neural Networks by Preventing Co-Adaptation of Feature Detectors.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0580">https://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0580</a>.
</div></div></section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Deep neural nets with a large number of parameters are very powerful machine learning systems. However, overfitting is a serious problem in such networks. Large networks are also slow to use, making it difficult to deal with overfitting by combining the predictions of many different large neural nets at test time. Dropout is a technique for addressing this problem. The key idea is to randomly drop units (along with their connections) from the neural network during training. This prevents units from co-adapting too much. During training, dropout samples from an exponential number of different “thinned” networks. At test time, it is easy to approximate the effect of averaging the predictions of all these thinned networks by simply using a single unthinned network that has smaller weights. This significantly reduces overfitting and gives major improvements over other regularization methods. We show that dropout improves the performance of neural networks on supervised learning tasks in vision, speech recognition, document classification, and computational biology, obtaining state-of-the-art results on many benchmark data sets.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="review" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h2>
<p>, introduces the dropout technique as an innovative method to prevent overfitting in neural networks. Overfitting occurs when a model performs well on training data but poorly on unseen test data, particularly when dealing with a large number of parameters and limited training samples. The paper addresses this by proposing the use of dropout, a regularization technique that randomly omits units (neurons) during training.</p>
</section>
<section id="core-ideas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="core-ideas">Core Ideas</h2>
<p>The central concept behind dropout is to prevent co-adaptation of feature detectors. In a traditional neural network, feature detectors can co-adapt to specific patterns in the training data, which leads to poor generalization. By randomly omitting neurons with a probability of 0.5 during training, each neuron is forced to contribute independently to the final output. This reduces the reliance on specific sets of neurons and ensures that each feature detector learns useful patterns.</p>
<p>Another significant advantage of dropout is that it acts as an efficient form of model averaging. Training with dropout can be seen as training an ensemble of neural networks that share parameters, making it computationally feasible to obtain better generalization without having to train multiple models.</p>
</section>
<section id="experimental-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="experimental-results">Experimental Results</h2>
<p>The authors demonstrate the effectiveness of dropout on several benchmark datasets, including MNIST, CIFAR-10, ImageNet, TIMIT, and the Reuters corpus.</p>
<ul>
<li>MNIST: Dropout reduced the error rate from 160 errors to around 110 by applying 50% dropout to hidden units and 20% dropout to input units.</li>
<li>TIMIT: Dropout improved frame classification accuracy in speech recognition tasks, reducing the error rate by 3% in comparison to standard training methods.</li>
<li>CIFAR-10: The authors achieved a 16.6% error rate without dropout and 15.6% with dropout, outperforming previous state-of-the-art results.</li>
<li>ImageNet: Dropout applied to deep convolutional neural networks (CNNs) reduced the error rate from 48.6% to 42.4%.</li>
<li>Reuters Corpus: Dropout reduced classification error from 31.05% to 29.62%.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="theoretical-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="theoretical-contributions">Theoretical Contributions</h2>
<p>The theoretical underpinning of dropout is grounded in model averaging and regularization. In standard practice, model averaging is performed by training multiple models and averaging their predictions, but this approach is computationally expensive. Dropout provides a far more efficient alternative by implicitly training an ensemble of models that share parameters, thus achieving the benefits of model averaging without the overhead of training separate models.</p>
<p>Additionally, dropout mitigates the problem of overfitting by introducing noise during training, making the model more robust. At test time, all units are used, but their outgoing weights are scaled to reflect the fact that fewer units were active during training.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussion-and-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion-and-impact">Discussion and Impact</h2>
<p>The introduction of dropout represents a major step forward in the development of deep learning models, as it allows for better generalization across a variety of tasks. Its simplicity, coupled with its effectiveness, has made dropout a standard tool in neural network training. The experiments conducted in the paper demonstrate its utility across a wide range of tasks, from image recognition to speech processing, providing compelling evidence of its broad applicability.</p>
<p>The idea of preventing co-adaptation of feature detectors to improve generalization is an elegant solution to a longstanding problem in neural network training. By ensuring that each neuron must work independently, dropout forces the model to learn more robust features that generalize well to unseen data.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This paper is a highly influential paper that introduced a novel technique for improving the generalization of deep learning models. The results speak for themselves, with dropout achieving state-of-the-art performance across multiple datasets and tasks. The technique has since become a standard part of neural network training, revolutionizing the field and contributing to the success of deep learning in real-world applications.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Improving {Neural} {Networks} by {Preventing} {Co-Adaptation}
    of {Feature} {Detectors}},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/dropout/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. n.d. <span>“Improving Neural Networks by Preventing
Co-Adaptation of Feature Detectors.”</span> <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/dropout/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/dropout/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/dropout/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:01:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ImageNet Classification with Deep Convolutional Neural Networks</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/imagenet/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="krizhevsky2012imagenet">(Krizhevsky, Sutskever, and Hinton 2012)</span> is a seminal paper in the field of deep learning. It introduced the AlexNet architecture, which won the ImageNet Large Scale Visual Recognition Challenge in 2012. The paper is a great starting point for anyone interested in deep learning, as it provides a detailed explanation of the architecture and training process of the network.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="krizhevsky2012imagenet">(Krizhevsky, Sutskever, and Hinton 2012)</span> titled “ImageNet Classification with Deep Convolutional Neural Networks”, the authors Alex Krizhevsky, Ilya Sutskever, and Geoffrey Hinton presents the development and training of a large deep convolutional neural network (CNN) for image classification using the ImageNet dataset.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-krizhevsky2012imagenet" class="csl-entry">
Krizhevsky, Alex, Ilya Sutskever, and Geoffrey E Hinton. 2012. <span>“Imagenet Classification with Deep Convolutional Neural Networks.”</span> <em>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</em> 25.
</div></div><p>Thus paper marks a pivotal point in the development of deep learning, particularly in the realm of computer vision. The authors introduced a large convolutional neural network (CNN) trained on the ImageNet dataset, which significantly outperformed previous models, winning the <a href="https://www.image-net.org/challenges/LSVRC">ImageNet Large Scale Visual Recognition Challenge</a> (ILSVRC) in 2012 with a top-5 test error rate of 15.3%.</p>
<section id="key-contributions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-contributions">Key Contributions:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Architecture</strong>: The CNN consists of five convolutional layers and three fully connected layers, with the final layer being a softmax classifier that distinguishes between 1000 categories. This architecture involves a total of 60 million parameters and 650,000 neurons.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>GPU Utilization</strong>: Training was performed on two GTX 580 GPUs to speed up the process, allowing them to handle the large network size and dataset. This took approximately 5-6 days to complete.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Techniques to Improve Performance</strong>: The network used a variety of novel techniques to improve both performance and training time:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rectified Linear Units</strong> (ReLUs): These non-saturating neurons were employed to speed up training, which was crucial for dealing with such a large model.</li>
<li><strong>Dropout</strong>: A regularization method was used in fully connected layers to prevent overfitting by randomly dropping some neurons during training.</li>
<li><strong>Data Augmentation</strong>: The authors employed various forms of data augmentation, including random crops, horizontal flips, and color variation via principal component analysis (PCA), which greatly expanded the size of the training set and further reduced overfitting.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>overfitting.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="results-and-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="results-and-impact">Results and Impact</h2>
<p>The network trained for the ILSVRC 2010 and 2012 challenges achieved top-1 and top-5 error rates of 37.5% and 17.0%, respectively, for ILSVRC 2010, far surpassing previous methods based on feature extraction and boosting. In the ILSVRC 2012 competition, the network reduced the top-5 error to 15.3%, compared to the 26.2% achieved by the second-best entry. This result not only established CNNs as the state-of-the-art model for image classification tasks but also cemented the importance of deep learning in the broader machine learning community.</p>
</section>
<section id="challenges-and-limitations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-and-limitations">Challenges and Limitations</h2>
<p>The authors acknowledge that their network size was constrained by the available GPU memory and that improvements in both hardware and larger datasets could potentially improve the performance of such models in the future.</p>
<p>The CNN’s architecture and optimization techniques pioneered by this paper have set a foundation for subsequent advances in deep learning, particularly in image recognition tasks.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The paper demonstrated the feasibility and efficacy of training deep networks on large-scale datasets and provided key insights into architectural choices, regularization, and optimization. This work has since inspired a plethora of follow-up research, leading to advancements such as transfer learning, fine-tuning on smaller datasets, and the further development of GPU-based training methods. The innovations introduced in this paper laid the groundwork for the modern AI revolution in image recognition and beyond.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {ImageNet {Classification} with {Deep} {Convolutional}
    {Neural} {Networks}},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/imagenet/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. n.d. <span>“ImageNet Classification with Deep
Convolutional Neural Networks.”</span> <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/imagenet/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/imagenet/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2012/imagenet/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:01:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Handwriting beautification using token means</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div id="fig-1" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-1-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="./fig_1.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Figure&nbsp;1: beautification"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/fig_1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-1-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: beautification
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="Zitnick2013Beautification">(Zitnick 2013)</span> the author shows how we can use a model for beautifying handwriting. The problem raised is that there is lots of variation in handwriting for a single individual and come up this a method to reduce this by a clever form of avaraging.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Zitnick2013Beautification" class="csl-entry">
Zitnick, C. Lawrence. 2013. <span>“Handwriting Beautification Using Token Means.”</span> <em>ACM Trans. Graph.</em> 32 (4). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/2461912.2461985">https://doi.org/10.1145/2461912.2461985</a>.
</div></div><p>The data is captured from a tablet and thus had a three dimensional structure. Central to this paper is are two ideas:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How to effectively average similar tokens to get a suitable mean token.
<ul>
<li>they use a moving window</li>
<li>the sample using a curvature based sampling
<ul>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="Whitney1937Regular">(Whitney 1937)</span></li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="mokhtarian1992theory">(Mokhtarian and Mackworth 1992)</span></li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="dudek1997shape">(Dudek and Tsotsos 1997)</span></li>
</ul></li>
<li>they use a fine alignment using
<ul>
<li>affinity matrix</li>
<li>dynamic programming to find the best warping between two sequences.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>they also use a visual similarity metric to make the model more <strong>robust</strong> to graphemes with similar strokes but different shapes.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>How to decide which tokens are similar.</li>
</ol>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-Whitney1937Regular" class="csl-entry">
Whitney, Hassler. 1937. <span>“On Regular Closed Curves in the Plane.”</span> <em>Compositio Mathematica</em> 4: 276–84. <a href="http://www.numdam.org/item/CM_1937__4__276_0/">http://www.numdam.org/item/CM_1937__4__276_0/</a>.
</div><div id="ref-mokhtarian1992theory" class="csl-entry">
Mokhtarian, Farzin, and Alan K Mackworth. 1992. <span>“A Theory of Multiscale, Curvature-Based Shape Representation for Planar Curves.”</span> <em>IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</em> 14 (8): 789–805.
</div><div id="ref-dudek1997shape" class="csl-entry">
Dudek, Gregory, and John K Tsotsos. 1997. <span>“Shape Representation and Recognition from Multiscale Curvature.”</span> <em>Computer Vision and Image Understanding</em> 68 (2): 170–89.
</div></div><p>Once these are solved, it becomes a matter of clustering tokens by similarity and then averaging the tokens in each cluster to get a mean token.</p>
<p>The mean token are then used to replace the original token in the handwriting data. The authors show that this method can be used to improve the quality of handwriting data.</p>
<p>Q. As time goes by there is more data and the replacements pool towards the cluster avarage. It seems that replacement might be more uniform if the earlier replacements were updated as their cluster avarage drifts…</p>
<p>This naturally leads to a kind of time series.</p>
<p>Perhaps the key idea is how the authors convert the text to a sequence of vectors use a token mean to represent the data. This is a simple idea but</p>
</section>
<section id="the-approach" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-approach">3. The approach</h2>
<p>We represent the stylus’s samples by storing the difference vectors between the stylus positions</p>
<p>i.e.&nbsp;<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CPhi%20=%20%5C%7B%5Cphi_1,%20%5Cldots%20,%20%5Cphi_a%5C%7D"> with</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cphi_i%20=%20%5C%7Bx_i,%20y_i,%20p_i%5C%7D"></p>
<p>where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(x_i,%20y_i)"> is the difference in the stylus’s pixel position between samples i − 1 and i.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p_i"> is the stylus’s pressure.</p>
</section>
<section id="stroke-resampling" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stroke-resampling">3.1 Stroke resampling</h2>
<p>As I understand it data is captured uniformly from a tablet and thus had a three dimensional structure. The authors then to resample the data to more faithfully represent the the curvature that is the building block of strokes within the handwriting.</p>
<div id="fig-2" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-2-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="./fig_2.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Figure&nbsp;2: stroke resampling - uniform v.s. curvature based"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/fig_2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-2-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: stroke resampling - uniform v.s. curvature based
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>They represent samples taken at regular distance intervals using <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CPhi%5Ed%20=%20%5C%7B%20%5Cphi%5Ed%20_1%20,%20%5Cldots,%20%5Cphi%5Ed_n%20%5C%7D"> where the sample magnitude <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r_i"> is constant for all samples. c.f. Figure&nbsp;2</p>
<p>Curvature based sampling:</p>
<p>We compute a stroke representation <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CE%A6%5Ec%20=%20%5C%7B%5Cphi%5Ec_1,%20%5Cldots%20,%20%5Cphi%5Ec_n%5C%7D"> with the same parameterization as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CE%A6">, i.e.&nbsp;<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CF%86%5Ec_i%20=%5C%7Bx_i,%20y_i,%20p_i%20%5C%7D"></p>
<p><span id="eq-stroke"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Az_i=z_%7Bi-1%7D+min(1,%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Calpha%20%5CDelta_%5Ctheta%20%5Cbeta_j%7D%7B2%5Cpi%7D)%20%5Cqquad%0A%5Ctag%7B1%7D"></span></p>
<p>where:</p>
<ul>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?z_i"> is the point on the curve.</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?z_%7Bi-1%7D"> is the previous point on the curve.</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Calpha"> is the sampling density parameter (minimum value = 24)</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta_%5Ctheta%20%5Cin%20(0,%5Cpi%5D"> is the angle between samples <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CF%86_%7Bi%E2%88%921%7D"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CF%86_i"></li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r_j"> is the stroke magnitude.</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta_j%20=%20max(0,%20min(1,%20r_j%20%E2%88%92%20%5Csqrt%7B2%7D))."> is a parameter that controls for discretization of the stylus.</li>
</ul>
<!-- todo try to understand this better find/create an implementation -->
</section>
<section id="refining-strokes" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="refining-strokes">3.2 Refining strokes</h2>
<p>When a user writes they generate a large set of stroke samples, denoted <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CE%A6"> (for the rest of the paper we assume a curvature-based sampling and drop the superscript c.) From <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CE%A6"> we create overlapping fixed length sequences of stroke samples called tokens c.f. Figure&nbsp;1. Each token contains n stroke samples.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
matrix profiles
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Using matrix profiles math behind stumpy might be usefull in making this work faster and better, not sure about real time.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="fine-scale-alignment" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fine-scale-alignment">Fine-scale alignment</h3>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fig-3" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-3-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="./fig_3.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Figure&nbsp;3: fine alignment"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/fig_3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-3-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;3: fine alignment
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div><p>The <strong>match cost</strong> <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta_%7Bk,l%7D"> is found using a linear combination of three features,</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbeta_%7Bk,l%7D%20=%20%5CDelta_%7B%5Chat%20r%7D%20+%20%5CDelta_%5Ctheta%20+%20%5Cdelta_p%20%5Cqquad%0A"></p>
<p>computed from:</p>
<ul>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_%7Bi,k%7D"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t_%7Bj,l%7D">.</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20%5Chat%20r"> is the absolute difference between <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%20r_k"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%20r_l">.</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta_%5Ctheta"> is the absolute angular distance between <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CE%B8_k"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%CE%B8_l">.</li>
<li><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cdelta_p"> measures if both strokes have consistent visibility. That is, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cdelta_p%20=%201"> if <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p_k%20=%200"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p_l%20=%200">, or <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p_k%20%3E%200"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p_l%20%3E%200">, and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cdelta_p%20=%200"> otherwise.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="merging-stroke-sets" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="merging-stroke-sets">Merging stroke sets</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Once two or more tokens are aligned, we can merge them by averaging the stroke samples.</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fig-4" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-4-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<a href="./fig_4.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Figure&nbsp;4: matches"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/fig_4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250"></a>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-4-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;4: matches
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div></section>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="see-also" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="see-also">See also</h2>
<ul>
<li>http://larryzitnick.org/</li>
</ul>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {Handwriting Beautification Using Token Means},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. n.d. <span>“Handwriting Beautification Using Token
Means.”</span> <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/HandwritingBeautification/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:01:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NIN — Network in Network</title>
  <dc:creator>Oren Bochman</dc:creator>
  <link>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="tldr" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="lin2014networknetwork">(Lin, Chen, and Yan 2014)</span> the authors, Lin, Min, Qiang Chen, and Shuicheng Yan, of this paper titled “Network in Network” paper came up with a way of connencting somee ideas on improving CNNs which had been mostly getting bigger <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(VGG%20%3E%20AlexNet%20%3E%20LeNet)"> . They replaced traditional linear filters in convolutional neural networks (CNNs) with multilayer perceptrons (MLPs) to enhance local feature abstraction. <mark>This new architecture, called NIN, also introduces <strong>global average pooling</strong> in place of <em>fully connected layers</em> thus reducing overfitting, improving model interpretability and more significantly reducing the size of the network.</mark></p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div><p>It took a while for the idea to catch on, but in computer vision, most of the parameters are in the fully connected layers, and the NIN architecture enables us to to reduce the number of parameters in the fully connected layers thereby <mark>breaking the curse of dimensionality in CNN</mark>. Once people realized this the NIN architecture became more widely adopted and influenced the development of more sophisticated deep learning architectures like the <mark>Inception architecture</mark> and further refined into the Resnet architecture</p>
<p>The NIN architecture has a significant impact on the design of CNNs by demonstrating that local feature abstraction can be enhanced with MLPs, leading to better performance with fewer parameters. Global average pooling, which replaces fully connected layers, makes the architecture more robust to overfitting and spatial translations, making it a powerful tool for image classification tasks. This combination of techniques has influenced the development of more sophisticated deep learning architectures, particularly in domains where model interpretability and reduced overfitting are critical.</p>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We propose a novel deep network structure called “Network In Network” (NIN) to enhance model discriminability for local patches within the receptive field. The conventional convolutional layer uses linear filters followed by a nonlinear activation function to scan the input. Instead, we build micro neural networks with more complex structures to abstract the data within the receptive field. We instantiate the micro neural network with a multilayer perceptron, which is a potent function approximator. The feature maps are obtained by sliding the micro networks over the input in a similar manner as CNN; they are then fed into the next layer. Deep NIN can be implemented by stacking multiple of the above described structure. With enhanced local modeling via the micro network, we are able to utilize global average pooling over feature maps in the classification layer, which is easier to interpret and less prone to overfitting than traditional fully connected layers. We demonstrated the state-of-the-art classification performances with NIN on CIFAR-10 and CIFAR-100, and reasonable performances on SVHN and MNIST datasets.</p>
<p>– <span class="citation" data-cites="lin2014networknetwork">(Lin, Chen, and Yan 2014)</span></p>
</blockquote><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"></div></div>
</section>
<section id="review" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h2>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="lin2014networknetwork">(Lin, Chen, and Yan 2014)</span> the authors introduced a novel deep learning architecture that aims to improve the abstraction capabilities of convolutional neural networks (CNNs) by incorporating multilayer perceptrons (MLPs) into the convolution layers. This approach, termed “Network in Network,” replaces the conventional linear filters used in CNNs with small neural networks, allowing for better local feature modeling. The NIN architecture also introduces global average pooling as a substitute for traditional fully connected layers to reduce overfitting and improve the interpretability of the model.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="ref-lin2014networknetwork" class="csl-entry">
Lin, Min, Qiang Chen, and Shuicheng Yan. 2014. <span>“Network in Network.”</span> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1312.4400">https://arxiv.org/abs/1312.4400</a>.
</div></div></section>
<section id="key-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-contributions">Key Contributions</h2>
<p>The NIN paper makes several key contributions to the deep learning landscape:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Mlpconv Layer</strong>: Instead of using traditional linear filters, NIN proposes the use of multilayer perceptrons (MLPs) within the convolutional layers (termed mlpconv layers). These layers act as universal function approximators, capable of modeling more complex representations within local receptive fields. This structure allows for better abstraction of non-linear latent concepts, overcoming the limitations of traditional linear filters in CNNs.</p>
<p><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/fig1.png" class="img-fluid"> <img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/fig2.png" class="img-fluid"></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Global Average Pooling</strong>: NIN introduces global average pooling as an alternative to fully connected layers in the final classification stage. This technique computes the spatial average of each feature map, feeding the result directly into a softmax layer for classification. By avoiding fully connected layers, the model becomes less prone to overfitting, thus improving generalization performance. Furthermore, this method provides more interpretable results by establishing a direct correspondence between feature maps and class labels.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>State-of-the-Art Performance</strong>: The authors demonstrate that NIN achieves state-of-the-art performance on several benchmark datasets, including CIFAR-10, CIFAR-100, and SVHN, without the need for extensive data augmentation or model ensembling. The architecture consistently outperforms other methods, such as maxout networks and CNNs with dropout regularization, especially in terms of classification accuracy.</p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./results.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Cifar-10 error rates"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/results.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%" alt="Cifar-10 error rates"></a></p>
<figcaption>Cifar-10 error rates</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="strengths" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strengths">Strengths</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Innovative Architecture</strong>: The introduction of MLPs into convolutional layers is a simple yet effective modification that significantly enhances the representational power of the model. This makes NIN a powerful alternative to traditional CNNs, especially for tasks that require fine-grained feature extraction and abstraction.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reduced Overfitting</strong>: The use of global average pooling not only replaces the computationally expensive fully connected layers but also serves as a built-in regularizer, reducing the need for additional techniques like dropout. This structural regularization helps to prevent overfitting, particularly on datasets with limited training examples, such as CIFAR-100.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Better Interpretability</strong>: The global average pooling layer allows for easier interpretation of the learned feature maps, as each map is directly associated with a class. This increases the transparency of the network’s the decision-making process compared to conventional CNNs.</p></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./fig4.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Visulization"><img src="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/fig4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%" alt="Visulization"></a></p>
<figcaption>Visulization</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="limitations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="limitations">Limitations</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Limited Novelty in Pooling</strong>: While global average pooling is effective, the concept is not entirely new, and its novelty is limited. Previous works have proposed similar techniques for specific tasks. However NIN certainly demonstrates the concepts efficacy.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Scalability</strong>: The paper focuses primarily on relatively small datasets like CIFAR-10, CIFAR-100, SVHN, and MNIST. While NIN excels in these scenarios, it would be interesting to see how the architecture performs on larger, more complex datasets such as ImageNet, where the size and variety of the data might pose additional challenges.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Lack of Depth Exploration</strong>: While the architecture consists of three stacked mlpconv layers, the paper does not deeply explore the impact of adding more layers or experimenting with deeper NIN networks. Such exploration could provide insight into how well the architecture scales with increased model depth.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>NIN architecture is an elegant and effective solution to improving feature abstraction and reducing overfitting in CNNs. By embedding MLPs within convolutional layers and using global average pooling for classification, NIN achieves state-of-the-art performance across a variety of tasks. NIN presented a strong case for the importance of local feature modeling and interpretable classification mechanisms in modern deep learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-paper" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-paper">The paper</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./paper.pdf" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="paper"><embed src="./paper.pdf" class="col-page" width="800" height="1000"></a></p>
<figcaption>paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfNvhP6k6ZM">Alex Smola Course Video on NIN</a>, his <a href="https://c.d2l.ai/stanford-cs329p/">course</a> and <a href="https://www.d2l.ai/">book</a></li>
</ul>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{bochman,
  author = {Bochman, Oren},
  title = {NIN -\/-\/- {Network} in {Network}},
  url = {https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-bochman" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Bochman, Oren. n.d. <span>“NIN --- Network in Network.”</span> <a href="https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/">https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://orenbochman.github.io/reviews/2013/NIN/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 12:01:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
